<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Misericors, mikrokosmos, or, Medeleys offices containing an iniunction to all duties of mercy belonging to the whole man.</title>
            <author>Medeley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 125 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114230</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849456</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07387)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1523:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Misericors, mikrokosmos, or, Medeleys offices containing an iniunction to all duties of mercy belonging to the whole man.</title>
                  <author>Medeley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 236 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. B[eale],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Second word of main title transliterated from the Greek.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:1"/>
                  <p>Miſericors, ΜΙΚΡΟΚΟΣ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΜΟΣ, OR, <hi>Medeleyes</hi> Offices, Containing an iniunction to all duties of Mercy belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the whole Man.</p>
                  <q>Miſer eſto in corde mecum.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 12.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Reioyce with them that reioyce, weepe with them that weepe, and be of like affection one towards another.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Conſider theſe matters, conſult, and giue ſentence.</p>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>I. B.</hi> 1619.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE EDVVARD Lord <hi>Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Baron of <hi>Marleigh,</hi> L. Lieuetenant of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and one of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt Honourable Priuy Counſell, my ſingular good Lord; and to his moſt worthy aſſociate my very good Lady and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe: health, wealth, and euerlaſting happineſſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, there was a cuſtom among the Iewes, that ſuch dettors whoſe debts
<pb facs="tcp:14604:3"/>amounted their abilities to ſatiſfie, were to be ſold themſelues, their wiues and children to become ſlaues to content their Creditors. So calling to minde how farre I ſtand ingaged to your Honor, not onely for your great and daily bounty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue continually ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from time to time; but alſo in that you haue willingly furthered mee by your other many and ſundry fauours, when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion required: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth me to confeſſe that I alſo ſhould incurre the penaltie aboue ſaid; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:14604:3"/>no other meanes to cancell the obligation, wherein I reſt bound to your Lordſhip; and now in your Honors abſence, (aye me) I finde no other like minded towards me. Wherefore as one <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> a poore ſchollar of <hi>Socrates</hi> did; ſo I hauing nothing elſe, doe dedicate not onely my ſelfe, but whatſoeuer is of mine, wholy to your Lordſhips ſeruice: continually pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Lord would multiply his many and ſundry bleſſings and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon you, and yours in this life; and that hee would hereafter crowne
<pb facs="tcp:14604:4"/>you with glory, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe for euer, with his Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually bounden, <hi>T. M.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:4"/>
                  <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                     </hi> Am not Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) according to the ſaying of the Poet, <hi>Scribimus indoct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> docti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> poemata paſſim,</hi> That godly &amp; learned treatiſes of all ſorts abound; &amp; this conſideration might well haue ſtayed my penne from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Know therefore that not vaine glory, but a ſenſible fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low feeling of the wronges and iniurses offered to my brethren (by reaſon of a certaine imbred
<pb facs="tcp:14604:5"/>ſelfe-loue reigning for the moſt part in the heart of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor) hath ſtirred vp in me a ſetled reſolution, to caſt in my widdows mite (notwithſtanding the many rich guifts, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy workes of the more learned) into the Lords treaſury Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my onely ſcope and drift is to ſhew forth my forward and willing diſpoſition in labouring to repaire the ruins and decaies of loue and piety, which this age hath almoſt throwne flat on the ground: if Narciſſus like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> dote not to much vpon mine owne ſhaddow. Many thinks it ſufficient, if they can talke and diſpute of faith, if they be able to reaſon and diſcourſe in eloquent wordes of religion: when they haue ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to turne their talking into walking, their wordes into
<pb facs="tcp:14604:5"/>workes, and their profeſſion into practiſe.</p>
                  <p>For whereas we ſhould ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt our faith and loue of God, in our loue, charity, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards our neighbour, many notwithſtanding are now become ſo degenerate, and ſuch <hi>Non proficients</hi> in the Schoole of true Chriſtian inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, that in their actions they are malicious, enuying, cruell, deceitfull, contentious, male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, ſcandalous, haters of God, iniurious, without natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection, and mercileſſe. But wee haue not ſo learned Chriſt, neither can it be (what ſhew ſoeuer they make) that the loue of God ſhould reſt in that heart, where fraudulent, hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, malicious, and enuying Foxes haue made their dennes. <hi>For if a man ſay hee loueth
<pb facs="tcp:14604:6"/>God, and hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is a liar: for how can hee that loueth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom hee hath ſeene, loue God whom hee hath not ſeene?</hi> as ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Iohn.</hi> And hee that would know how to loue his neighbour aright, muſt firſt entertaine the loue of God in his heart; and the loue of God is retained by practiſing the loue of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For euen as the heate of the naturall body warmeth the cloathes that are put vpon it, which cloathes afterward nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and conſerue the naturall heate: ſo the fire of the loue of God, which ſpringeth of faith, kindleth the heart with the loue of thy neighbour, and the loue of our neighbour cheriſheth the loue of God in our harts. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if theſe endeauours of mine
<pb facs="tcp:14604:6"/>ſhall effect any good, it is the thing that I deſire; and let God haue the praiſe: if not, yet I haue diſcharged my conſcience. Therefore I humbly beſeech thee into whoſe hands theſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſhall come, throughly to reade them at thy leaſure, and to marke them well; begin not onely, but make an end: for hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily the beſt wine is reſerued till the laſt. And the God of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and conſolation, make vs followers of God as deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and grant that we be like minded one towards another, after the example of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in Chriſt,</hi> Thomas Medeley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14604:7"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14604:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>MISERICORS, Or</hi> Motiues to mercy.</head>
                  <div type="preface">
                     <head>The Preface.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the yong man in the Goſpell, that was deſirous to obtaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, yet being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned by our bleſſed Sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to ſell what he had and giue to the poore, departed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14604:8"/>ſorrowfull that Heauen ſhould bee held at ſo high a rate. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. So (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) are there many in theſe our daies, that very willingly would bee regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred among the number of the ſaithfull, righteous, and mercifull men, whoſe chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s can abide no beggers. For who amongſt vs is there almoſt, that doth any good, or what man is he amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt a thouſand, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a fellow feeling of the miſeries of his bretheren, remembreth the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> Yet our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> exhorteth all thoſe that wil be his Diſciples to the practiſe of mercy, after the example of our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father.<note place="margin">Luk. 6.36.</note> 
                        <hi>Ye ſhall therefore bee mercifull, as your Father
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14604:8"/>which is in Heauen, is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are two principall points to bee conſidered in this text: Firſt, a precept, <hi>Ye ſhall therefore be mercifull,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the preſident; <hi>As your heauenly Father is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> of theſe in order.</p>
                     <p>Mercifull men may bee taken two waies, <hi>Paſſiuely,</hi> and <hi>Actiuely: Paſſiuely,</hi> for ſuch as God hath receiued to mercy,<note place="margin">Tim. 1.13.</note> as he did the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul; becauſe hee ſinned ignorantly, through vnbeleife:</hi> and in this reſpect,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.23.</note> they are tearmed <hi>Veſſels of mercy, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to glory;</hi> of this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are onely thoſe which repent and amend.<note place="margin">Pro. 28.13</note> As <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper, but hee that confeſſeth, and forſaketh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14604:9"/>them, ſhall haue mercy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But in this place it is meant <hi>Actiuely</hi> namely, for ſuch as ſhew mercy vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Now that we may the better know our duties in this point, let vs more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſider what the workes of mercy are. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas</hi> very learnedly ſetteth them forth, to bee in number, 13.6. belonging to the ſoule, &amp; 7. to the body, comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in two <hi>verſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Conſule, Caſtiga, Solare, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte for Ora;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vifito, Poto, Cibo, Redimo, Tego, Coligo, Condo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Inſtruct the Ignorant, Correct the ſinfull, Comfort the ſorrowfull, Forgiue the offenders, Beare with the weak, and Pray for all men. Theſe are workes of mercy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14604:9"/>to the ſoule, Viſit the ſicke, Giue drinke to the thirſty, bread to the hungry, helpe the opreſſed, cloath the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, Lodge the harbourles, and bury the dead: Theſe to the body, of them particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, more at large.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Conſule.</head>
                     <p>The firſt worke of mercy to the ſoule, is to inſtruct the Ignorant, this duty is both <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſticall; Eccleſiaſticall</hi> diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, chiefly concerneth thoſe whom God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ouer vs in the Church, as Biſhops, Miniſters, &amp;c. <hi>Domeſtical</hi> diſcipline belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth to Fathers, &amp; Maſters of families. That part of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction which appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the Miniſters &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14604:10"/>of the Church, is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, <hi>Catechumenicall,</hi> and <hi>Propheticall.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Catechumonicall</hi> document,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.</note> 
                        <hi>Is the Doctrines of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Chriſt,</hi> wherby Gods children are led forwards to wards perfection, which we vſually cal catechiſing. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical</hi> inſtruction, is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with Doctrines, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications drawn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, for our further growth in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Domeſticall or Paternall diſcipline is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded of God.<note place="margin">De. 11.19.</note> 
                        <hi>You ſhall teach them your children, ſpeae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them, when thou ſitteſt in thy houſe, and when thou walkeſt in the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp. Saint Paul</hi> likewiſe willeth the <hi>Epheſians to bring
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14604:10"/>vp their children inſtructed in the feare of the Lord;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eph. 6.4.</note> this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to be performed three manner of waies, by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by precepts of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and by correction.</p>
                     <p>By example, our Lord &amp; Saulour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> taught vs when hee ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.5.</note> 
                        <hi>Firſt caſt out the beame, that is in thine owne eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee more clearely, the more that is in thy brothers eye:</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians <hi>To walke wiſely,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Col. 4.5.</note> 
                        <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, that are without.</hi> For youth is generally more corrupted by the ill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels <hi>of Parents, Maiſters, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, or Miniſters,</hi> then for the moſt part any good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, exhortation, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from others, can well amend them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14604:11"/>naturally proane to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the worſt preſidents: &amp; herein may they iuſtly be tearmed <hi>Rehoboams</hi> ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; who whereas he might haue learned much wiſdom out of his Father <hi>Salomons</hi> ſentences, and actions, yet could hee gather nothing worthy of imitation from them,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 10.12.</note> but <hi>Where as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taxed his ſubiects ouer greeuouſly, he would therein goe beyond him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So are there many <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> amongſt vs, in theſe our dayes, who can find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy their imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of the good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, vertuous precepts, and diuine exhortations of their Parents, Maſters and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or Miniſters, but if they haue any vice, blemiſh,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14604:11"/>imperfection, or corruption therein they will be ſure to follow, and exceede their Preſident. For ſuch is the corruption of the time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and age wherein we liue, that in any good thing wee come ſhort of our preſident, but in euill things wee exceede our patterne; yet ought we not ſo to doe, but rather in all examples, to behaue our ſelues according to the counſell of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tit. 2.8.</note> 
                        <hi>That hee which withſtandeth, may bee aſhamed, hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning vs, to ſpeake euill of.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, youth are alſo to be inſtructed in precepts of diſcipline, which <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> auoucheth, ſaying,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.6.</note> 
                        <hi>Teach a child in the trade of his way, and when he is old, hee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14604:12"/>ſhall not depart from it:</hi> In their prime and tender age, they ought (as <hi>Samuels</hi>) to be dedicated to the Lord, to ſound forth the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name of the moſt high, and then as the <hi>Poet ſaith: Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens, ſeruabit odorem, teſta diu,</hi> they being at the firſt well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, will continue the better.</p>
                     <p>But herein many are greatly to be reproued, that whereas they ought eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to haue a care, that their Children ſhould (as ſoone as they can ſpeake with the leaſt vſe of vnderſtanding) be ſeaſoned with the liquor of grace, and good nurture. <hi>They with the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſes teach traditions,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mark 7.13</note> 
                        <hi>which they themſelues haue ordained,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14604:12"/>and make the Word of God of none authority.</hi> They will teach them to lie, to ſweare, to ſpeake filthy ſpeeches, and to ſing ſongs of ribal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, but the duties of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the practiſe of pietie, the <hi>Catechumenicall</hi> Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of faith, and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points of ſaluation, they account not worthy the learning, as vnfit for their tender yeares and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity; yet this affection was not in <hi>Abraham,</hi> of whom the Lord ſaith, <hi>I know that he will command his ſonnes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note> 
                        <hi>and his houſhold after him, to doe righteouſneſſe and iudgement, and to keepe the way of the Lord, that the Lord may bring vpon Abraham all that hee hath ſpoken vnto him. Ioſua was alſo reſolued,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioſ. 24.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14604:13"/>whatſoeuer others did, yet hee, and his houſhold would ſerue the Lord.</hi> And ſurely in this caſe, it behooueth great men eſpecially to be good men, as being vnprinted ſtatutes, and ſpeaking lawes vnto the reſt. <hi>Let vs therfore be mercifull, as our heauenly Father is mercifull.</hi> And thus much touching the firſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mercy to the ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Caſtiga.</head>
                     <p>THE ſecond worke of mercy to the ſoule, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in correcting the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: This duty is <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Domeſticall,</hi> and <hi>Iudicial. Eccleſiaſticall</hi> correction is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Biſhops &amp; Miniſtres of the Church, according to their ſeuerall functions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, or correct vice in any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14604:13"/>of the flocke of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge. For ſaith <hi>Saint Paul,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> 
                        <hi>the whole Scripture is giuen by inſpiration from God, and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to inſtruct, and correct in rightcouſneſſe, that the man of God may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Saul deſerued commendations,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.24</note> 
                        <hi>becauſe he humbled himſelfe at the rebuke of the Prophet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel. Dauid ſuffered gently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of the Prophet Nathan;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.7.</note> neither did <hi>Ahab diſdaine to heare his faults told him from the mouth of Eliah.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.20.</note> And thus wee ſee how patiently in times paſt, euen the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt would heare of their faults; albeit in theſe dayes ſuch wickedneſſe now reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that ſcarſe the meaneſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14604:14"/>will put vp checke, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule, being like them of whom the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">Hoſe. 4.4.</note> that <hi>they reproue the Prieſts, telling them that they haue nothing to doe with them, they ſhall not anſwere for their faults, they know what they haue to doe as well as any hee, whoſoeuer ſhall reproue them.</hi> Theſe, or the like words, will euery rude ruffin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to vs, whenſoeuer hee ſhall bee taxed for any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanor: Yet ſaith Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.17.</note> 
                        <hi>Thouſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but thou ſhalt plainely rebuke thy neighbour, and ſuffer him not to ſinne.</hi> As if hee ſhould haue ſaid; Hee that ſuffereth his friend to goe on in his wickedneſſe, vnreproued, ſheweth therein rather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14604:14"/>then any true loue vnto him. Very well therefore ſaith <hi>Seneca; Qui non vetat peccare, cum poſſit, Iubet.</hi> Hee that ſuffereth ſinne vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled, doth as it were command it.</p>
                     <p>But rightly to reprehend, is one of the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties incident to humane diſcretion.</p>
                     <p>And yet it is eaſier known then done, partly by reaſon of the way wardneſſe of the delinquents diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that may not ſuffer reproofe, partly by reaſon of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers affections of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers themſelues, whom ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorance diſables, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour withdrawes, feare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terres, or fury tranſports be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14604:15"/>
                     <p>Firſt, ſuch (I ſay) is the waywardnes of mans croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nature, that (for the moſt part) they may not heare of their offences, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of <hi>Herod, who heard Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt willingly,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> 
                        <hi>and did many things after him, but when hee told him that it was not lawfull for him to take Herodias h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> brother Philips wife, hee laide holde on him, and caſt him in priſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ieroboam alſo ſtretched out his hand from the Altar,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Kin. 13.4 &amp; 22.27.</note> 
                        <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lay hold on him, ſo ſoone as hee was reproued;</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah muſt bee fed with bread and water of affliction till A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab returne in peace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wee can enery one of vs cry out againſt the ſinnes of the time and age wherein
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14604:15"/>we liue, ſaying;<note place="margin">Hoſ 4.1.</note> 
                        <hi>There is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land.</hi> But what man is hee among a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, that in the true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of his owne ſoule, will ſtand out with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and ſay; <hi>Behold, I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yea, I haue done wickedly,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.17.</note> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> theſe ſheepe what haue they done?</hi> For albeit in generall we all confeſſe our ſelues to be ſinners, yet ſo great is the ſelfe-loue that euery man by nature carrieth in his owne boſome, that when it commeth to the particulars, he coueteth to lay the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon another mans ſhoulders, and not to ſay with <hi>Iudah, that he, or ſhee,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 38.16.</note> 
                        <hi>is more righteous then I.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A firſt part of <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Corrigidors there are,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14604:16"/>whom ignorance diſables, theſe poaſt vpon Gods meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, before they haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their errand, being more greedy of the gaine, then gainefull in the grace of their calling, hauing not as yet receiued any warning from the mouth of the Lord to giue to his people; and therefore no way fit to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the charge wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they haue thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
                     <p>There are a ſecond ſort, whom either fauour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes, or feare deterres from reprouing ſinne.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.15.</note> 
                        <hi>Such, who louing the world, loue net the Father;</hi> that is to ſay, when <hi>Michael</hi> your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or Peter Pleaſe-man his Curate, will not tell <hi>Ahab</hi> of his cruelty, <hi>Nabal</hi> of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14604:16"/>churliſhneſſe, <hi>Iezebel</hi> of her painting, <hi>Gehazi</hi> of bribery, &amp;c: leſt they thereat offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhould withdraw their affection from him, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure another. And thus whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt hee preferreth gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, honour before honeſty, and money more then the good of any: hee is ready euen with the falſe Prophets,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 22.15.</note> 
                        <hi>to bid Ahab goe vp and proſper.</hi> In ſtead of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting vices, he is ready to flatter and ſooth men vp in their conceited vertues, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering a ruſty blade with a veluet ſcabbard, and crying peace, peace, when warre is approaching; whereas Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God commandeth,<note place="margin">Eſai. 58.1.</note> 
                        <hi>Crie aloud, ſpare not, lift vp thy voice like a Trumpet, tell ludah his ſinnes, &amp; Iſrael their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14604:17"/>
                     <p>Shall God bid cry aloud, and ſhall we be ſilent?</p>
                     <p>A third ſort of corrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors there are, whom ſury tranſports beyond the bounds of reaſon thoſe men can winke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all things, till they themſelues be firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and then paſſing the bounds of charity, they lay all things open, yea, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture more then all, ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing their Pulpits with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues, and declamations, ſo farre are they tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the fury of their affections. And yet for all this, ſinne muſt bee checkt, errour muſt bee reſtrained, and vices muſt be ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, leſt vnder pretence of ſuppoſed defects, in our ſelues, or reſpects to others they gather head, and like
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14604:17"/>the vnruly Sea, break down the bankes, &amp; ouerwhelme the Land with <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and ſuperſtitious impiety. Thus much touching <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call correction.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Domeſticall correction</hi> is twofold, reproofe, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; this duty is to be performed by Parents, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their children, and by Maſters towards their ſeruants <hi>Salomon</hi> is very co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious in this matter,<note place="margin">Pro 23.13.</note> 
                        <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold not correction from thy child, thouſhalt ſmite him with the rod; and ſhalt deliuer his ſoule from hell. Correct thy ſonne, and he will giue thee reſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 29.17</note> 
                        <hi>and he will giue pleaſures to thy ſoule.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Pro. 13.24</note> 
                        <hi>He that ſpareth the rod, hateth his ſonne: but he that loueth him, correcteth him betimes.</hi> All which teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14604:18"/>tendes to this, that if we deſire our owne peace, and not to be moleſted, nor vexed, but much comforted by them, if we would teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our faithfull loue to them, if wee would purge their hearts from folly and ſinne, and preſerue their ſoules from euerlaſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then let vs bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to giue them due cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ordinance, to reforme and ſaue their ſoules.</p>
                     <p>Let all cockering Parents harken what the Lord ſaith to the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Eli</hi> for not correcting his children:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.12, 13.</note> 
                        <hi>In that day will I raiſe vp againſt Ely all things that. I haue ſpoken concerning his houſe, when I begin, I will alſo make an end: and I haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14604:18"/>tolde him that I will iudge his houſe for euer, for the iniquity which hee knoweth, becauſe his ſonnes ranne on in a ſlander, and hee ſtayed them not.</hi> So that you may ſee, how that the irreſpectiue conniuency of Parents vpon their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens faults, bringeth often times Gods iudgements v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the whole family, and not without great cauſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nam tenera eſt dum virga, recenſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> flectitur, huc, illuc vt vis; at poſt vbi creuit, non, rob u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta arbos:</hi> while the twig is tender and greene, it is bent hither &amp; thither as you wil; but after it is growne, you cannot, it will bee a ſtrong tree. And as Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fell vpon <hi>Ely</hi> and his Family for this ſinne:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.17, 18.</note> 
                        <hi>for Hophni and Phinehas died in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14604:19"/>the battell, and Ely at the newes thereof fell from his ſeat back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and brake his necke:</hi> ſo in theſe dayes many adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to execution for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Fellony, or the like, haue cryed out vpon their tender hearted Parents for bearing with them too much in their child-hood.</p>
                     <p>But whileſt I inſiſt vpon this point, I beſeech you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake me not; for my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that we ſhould haue an eye to the counſel of our Sauiour in this Text: ſo to ſhew mercy to others as we would expect the mercy of God towards our ſelues.</p>
                     <q>
                        <p>Si quoties peccant homines, ſua fulmina mittat</p>
                        <p>Iupiter: exiguo tempore iner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis erit.</p>
                     </q>
                     <p>For if that <hi>Ioue</hi> ſhould ſtrike</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14604:19"/>
                     <p>So oft as Men offend, The Poets ſay his Thunderbolts Would ſoone be at an end.</p>
                     <p>Thus much touching do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall correction.</p>
                     <p>Iudiciall correction is to bee performed by Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates towards the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: therefore thus ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Lord of Hoſts, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Execute true iudgement,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Zach. 7.9.10.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſhew mercy and compaſſion euery man to his brother; and oppreſſe not the widow, nor the fatherleſſe, the ſtranger, nor the poore, and let none of you imagine euill againſt his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his heart.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4</note> 
                        <hi>The Magiſtrate alſo beareth not the Sword in vaine: for he is the Miniſter of God, to take vengeance on him that doth euill.</hi> That Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate therefore that will be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14604:20"/>ſaid rightly to beare the ſword, muſt vnſheath it ſo againſt ſinne, and ſinners, that piety and good men may flouriſh the better, &amp; and proſper. And herein the pious care of good <hi>Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> is to bee highly extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:<note place="margin">2 Chro. 19.5.6.</note> 
                        <hi>For he ſet Iudges in the Land of</hi> Iudah <hi>throughout all the ſtronge Citties thereof, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ty: And ſaid vnto them, take heede what yee doe, for you execute not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man, but of the Lord, and he will bee with you in the cauſe, and iudgement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Magiſtrates in theſe times, are culpable in two points: firſt, that they doe not conſider they execute the Lords iudgements, or if they did, how then could your curſed ſwearer, your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14604:20"/>prophaner of Gods Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, &amp; beaſtly drunkards goe ſo vnpuniſhed, as for the moſt part they doe; yet herein they ſhew themſelus like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mark. 7.13</note> 
                        <hi>Who preferred their owne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, before Gods lawes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, your inferiour Magiſtrates are greatly to be blamed, in that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either too milde, or elſe too too negligent, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſmall offences and petty fellonies, in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall iuriſdictions, doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cauſe the offender to a greater Iudgement: ſo that whereas in pardoning ſmall faults, they would be eſteemed moſt mercifull, it often times falleth out far otherwiſe. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo to temper you iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14604:21"/>that in them you may remember mercy. To that end ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſa. 88.10.</note> 
                        <hi>Mercy and truth ſhall mcete together, righteouſneſſe and peace, ſhall kiſſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And as it was in <hi>Queen Elizabeths Poeſy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sit piger adpaenas princeps, adpraemia velox.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dolet: quoties cogitur eſſe ferox.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſee and hold my peace,</l>
                        <l>A Princely Poeſy right;</l>
                        <l>For euery fault ſhould not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke,</l>
                        <l>A Prince or man of might.</l>
                        <l>Then happy we that haue,</l>
                        <l>A King ſo well inclin'd;</l>
                        <l>That when as Iuſtice drawes his ſword,</l>
                        <l>Hath mercy in his minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Solare.</head>
                     <p>THe third worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy appertaining to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14604:21"/>ſoule, conſiſteth in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the ſorrowfull. This duty is <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> and Generall; <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, chiefly conſiſteth in pronouncing the glad tydings of the Goſpell, to thoſe whoſe conſciences by the law, are throughly wounded, for their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And ſurely they that thus ſow in teares,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſa 126.5</note> 
                        <hi>ſhall reape in ioy. For godly forrow cauſeth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10</note> not to be repented of</hi> And as this duty is to be inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all Miniſters at all times, ſo more eſpecially, are they to labour to bring al thoſe, on whom God hath laide his heauy rod of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, to a true ſight and feeling of their ſins, which is by the rule of Gods law;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14604:22"/>Secondly, to a feare of Gods anger for, them that they may lament them, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly repenting, call to God for mercy: Thirdly, let vs bring them to the true Samaritan, our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Who when the Prieſt and Leuite left vs wounded;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 10.33 24.</note> that is to ſay, the <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> and <hi>Iudiciall</hi> Law paſſed by vs; <hi>He bound vp our wounds, and paid for our curing, that wee might be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to euerlaſting happineſſe.</hi> Fourthly, we are ſo to arme them <hi>againſt the concupiſence of the fleſh,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.16</note> 
                        <hi>the luſt of the eyes, and pride of life,</hi> with the comfort of the Spirit, the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Angels, &amp; crownes of eternall glory; that they thus prepared to paſſe the waues of their trouble ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14604:22"/>ſickneſſe, might ſafely ariue at the port of their eternall bleſſedneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Generall conſolation is to be performed amongſt all Chriſtians mutually one towards another, which thing Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, ſaying:<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5 14.</note> 
                        <hi>Comfort the feeble minded.</hi> In the performance of this duty, let vs eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue an eye to the cauſe of the party greeued; for none can truely comfort an other, who hath not a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low feeling, of the miſerie, of his brother. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> therefore willeth vs,<note place="margin">Ro. 12.16.</note> to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with them that reioyce, and to weepe with them that weepe, and to be of like affection one towards another.</hi> All ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is for the moſt part drawne from one of theſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14604:23"/>foure heads: Greefe of conſcience, Feare of death, Loſſe of friends, And loſſe of wealth.</p>
                     <p>Greefe of conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from the knowledge of ſome hainous ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, for which the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender feareth Gods anger and iudgement, towards him.</p>
                     <p>And ſurely vntill (like wandring ſheepe, that haue gon aſtray) we acknowledg our ſelues, as loſt &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, through our dayly tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, we haue no hope in the true Lambe of God, to be purged from them; I ſay, hee that ſometimes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth not the abſence of Gods graces from him, ſhal neuer finde aſſured peace to his conſcience, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14604:23"/>of Gods holy Spirit. And this doth our bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe teſtifie, whereas he ſaith:<note place="margin">Mat 11.28</note> 
                        <hi>Come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, all yee that are weary, and heauy laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, all you that ſeeke eaſe in mee, muſt firſt be weary with the burthen of your ſinnes, as deſirous to leaue them; then you muſt alſo come laden with teares of hearty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, before you can find reſt vnto your ſoules, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon followeth that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of Almighty God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the <hi>Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiell;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Exc. 18.21.</note> 
                        <hi>At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinnes, from the bottome of his heart, I will put all his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out of my remembrance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But many Libertines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14604:24"/>this place of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> thinking that they may repent, when they liſt; albeit the Lord ſaith, <hi>At what time ſoeuer,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Exec. 18.21.</note> yet haſt thou no warrant from thence, to thinke that thou ſhalt haue free power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent whenſoeuer thou wilt. <hi>Poenitentia ſera rarovera.</hi> Late Repentance, is ſeldom true repentance; wee reade of one that repented at the laſt houre, becauſe no man ſhould diſpaire, and but of one, leſt any man ſhould preſume: we ſee many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of thoſe who haue deferred their repentance, haue beene taken away in their ſinnes, and died impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13</note> 
                        <hi>Put not off therefore from day to day, but turue to the Lord your God, becauſe he is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14604:24"/>mercifull, &amp; gracious, &amp; ſuch a one, as is ſorry for your afficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Say not with your ſelues as <hi>Came</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas,</hi> that your ſinnes cannot be pardoned. For ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiris Caine, maior eſt dei Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerecordia, quam omnis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na miſeria.</hi> Thou ſpeak eſt falſe <hi>Caine,</hi> men cannot bee ſo ſinfull, as God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if with penitent hearts they could call vpon him. A proofe of this may bee ſeene in the poore <hi>Publican, Who ſtandeth a farre off, and would not come neere, nor yet lift vp his eyes to heauen,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9</note> 
                        <hi>but ſmote his breaſt ſaying: God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> Hee would not come neere vnto God, therefore God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy commeth neere vnto him: for the text ſaith, <hi>Hee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14604:25"/>went away rather Iuſtified.</hi> Oh happy therefore, and thrice bleſſed are they, who gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnder the burthen of their ſinnes, ſeeke quietues of minde in Chriſt alone. Thus much touching greefe of Conſcience.</p>
                     <p>The next ſpeciall duty of conſolation is to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed toward thoſe, who ſtand in feare of death, wherein you are to require the aide of your Miniſter, &amp; with him, to ioyne in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to our heauenly Father, for the ſicke Patient, that if it ſo ſtand with his great goodneſſe, he may reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his former health; if not, yet to forgiue him his ſinnes, and ſo to arme him with patience, that he may the better bee prepared to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14604:25"/>enter into glory: And of this, ſufficient hath beene ſpoken, in the place of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall conſolation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the third place, wee are to ſpeake of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting of thoſe, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer immoderate greefe for the death of their friends, as wiues doe for the deaths of their husbands, children for their Parents, and one friend for the loſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>To whom I ſay, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to powre forth teares ouer the dead, for ſo did <hi>Iacob</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſuppoſing him to bee dead.<note place="margin">Ge. 37.35.</note> 
                        <hi>Surely, I will goe downe into the graue, to my Sonne mourning.</hi> And likewiſe great was the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, that <hi>Dauid</hi> made
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14604:26"/>when newes was brought him, of the death of <hi>Abſolon. Oh Abſolon my Sonne,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.35.</note> 
                        <hi>my Sonne Abſolon, would God I haddied for thee: Oh Abſolon my Sonne, my Sonne</hi> Nay, Chriſt himſelfe (ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome</hi>) went not to his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher without weeping eyes, yet ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> 
                        <hi>I would not haue you ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, concerning them which are aſleepe, that ye ſorrow not, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as others that haue no hope.</hi> And therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Barnard, Non culpamus affectum, ſed exceſſum.</hi> Wee blame not the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the want of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Hee that ſaid,<note place="margin">Eccle. 38.17.</note> my <hi>Sonne power forth thy teares, ouer the dead;</hi> ſaid alſo, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thy ſelfe.</hi> Amongſt other meane comforts (ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulllian</hi>)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14604:26"/>
                        <hi>Reſurrectio mortuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, fiducia Chriſtianorum;</hi> Chriſtians, who beleeue a Reſurrection to a better life, ſhould raiſe vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by faith from ſuch too dolefull paſſions; for as in all other things, ſo in this, a moderation ſhould bee had. Haſt thou loſt a good Father, Friend, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, Wife, or Child, ſay with the holy man <hi>Iob,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>The Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> They are not cleane taken from vs, but gon a little before on the way, wherin we muſt al follow; we ſhall all one day meete againe by the grace of God; at what time there will be no meane ioy, when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14604:27"/>friends ſhall for euer liue, reioyce, and ſing, an <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiah,</hi> to our heauenly King. And ſurely ſaith the prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſa. 57, 1.</note> 
                        <hi>They are taken away from the euil to come.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus a little before his paſſion, ſeeing his Diſciples ſorrowfull for his departure, which was ſo ſhortly to enſue; ſaid vnto them,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.29.</note> 
                        <hi>If you loued mee, you would reioyce becauſe I ſaid I goe to my Father.</hi> So if wee loued our friends, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but reioyce, becauſe they are gone to Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, their Redeemer. For they are taken from miſery to happineſſe, from vanity, to glory, and from fading pleaſures, to euerlaſting ioyes.</p>
                     <p>Let vs therefore rather
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14604:27"/>praiſe God for their ſo happy deliuerance, then any way ſeeme diſcontented thereat. Thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the death of our Friends. In the laſt place we are to comfort ſuch as haue ſuſtained loſſe of worldly wealth; which hapeneth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by caſualty of fire, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations of water, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, Pirates, or theeues: To al which kind of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſſes, theſe fiue princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples following, are to bee propounded.</p>
                     <p>Firſt conſider what our bleſſed Sauiour taught vs, when he willed vs to pray, <hi>That Gods will might be done in vs:</hi> what reaſon then hath any man, to withſtand the performance of that, for which hee dayly prayeth.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14604:28"/>And our Sauiour praying, a little before his paſſion, ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39</note> 
                        <hi>Neuertheleſſe not as I wil, but as thou wilt.</hi> Oh excellent Patterne for obedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, patiently to content themſelues with what croſs ſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe our hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly Father to lay vpon them.</p>
                     <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> conſider the <hi>Earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the round world, and they that dwell therein.</hi> If then all the riches of this world, belong to the Lord, who in mercy hath but lent them vs and made vs to be Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ouer them.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.1.</note> 
                        <hi>As by the Parable of the vniuſt Steward, may appeare:</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo auoucheth it, when he ſaith, <hi>Wee brought nothing into this World,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.7.</note> 
                        <hi>and it is certe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>, wee can
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14604:28"/>carry nothing out:</hi> Why then ſhould men bee too much deiected, ſeeing the Lord hath but taken his own, we cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him a very vnthankful debter, that is not as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pay, as to borrow. Man is the debter, God is the lender, let vs not herein deale with our heauenly Father, more vniuſtly then we would haue our Brother deale with vs. Let vs ſay with the holy man <hi>Iob,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>The Lord, giueth, the Lord taketh away; bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> When I had them, I was not the better, I truſted not to them, they therefore being gone, doe nothing diſmay mee.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, conſider the Lord hath done this for the tryall of our Faith, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14604:29"/>and perſeuerance, as he dealt with his ſeruant <hi>Iob</hi> who ſaid,<note place="margin">Iob. 13.15.</note> 
                        <hi>Though hee ſlay mee, yet I will truſt in his mercy,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For when the Lord ſhall perceiue that our confidence is not built vpon fading ioyes and tranſitory pleaſures, but firmely caſt vpon him, he then will drawe neere vnto vs, and vnto al that truly feare him, &amp; truſt in his mercy, as he did to his ſeruant <hi>Iob, To whom God gaue twice ſo much riches, as hee had taken from him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fourthly, call to minde the prouidence of God, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Creatures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Behold (ſaith our Sauiour) the fowles of heauen,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 6.26.</note> 
                        <hi>for they ſowe not, neither reape, nor carry into barnes, yet your heauenly Father feedeth them are you not much better then they?</hi> The Phyloſopher <hi>Bias</hi>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14604:29"/>caſt his goods into the Sea, &amp; being demanded why, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Omnia mea mecum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> My goods and I, are neuer parted. It were to be wiſhed in like manner, that Chriſtians would caſt away the leauen of too too worldly carefulneſſe, into the ſea of eternall forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to that end eſpecially, that Chriſt, and they might neuer be parted.</p>
                     <p>The fift and laſt principle, and not the leaſt, which wee are to performe to our poore brethren in this behalfe, is, to yeeld them our charitable releefe; for ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn, Who ſoeuer hath the worlds goods,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.17.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſeeth his brother haue neede, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him: or how can he be ſaid to loue God whom hee ſeeth not,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14604:30"/>when he loueth not his brother whom he daily ſeeth? Let vs therefore be mercifull, as our heauenly father is mercifull.</hi> Thus far of the third worke of mercy to the ſoule ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in comforting the ſorrowfull mentioned in this word <hi>Solare.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Remitte.</head>
                     <p>THe fourth worke of mercy towards the ſoule, conſiſteth in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and forgiuing, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. This duty, and the reſt that follow, are all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; euery man muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue all men, as our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus</hi> plainely ſhewed when he taught his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to pray,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.4.</note> 
                        <hi>Forgiue vs our ſinnes, for euen we forgiue euery man that is indebted to vs,</hi> as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14604:30"/>if he ſhould ſay, expect no forgiueneſſe at the hand of Almightie God, vnleſſe ye likewiſe freely from the bottome of your hearts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue one another: yet now a daies, among your ſwagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and roaring gallants, there is but a word and a wound, and among your ciuill &amp; lawleſſe Lawyers, but a word and a writ,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.32.</note> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe <hi>S.</hi> Paul <hi>willeth vs to be Courteous one towards an other, and tender hearted, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiuing one another, euen as God for Chriſts ſake, freely forgaue vs.</hi> Wherein the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle meeteth with an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection that might be made I am as gentle, quiet, affable curteous, and patient, as any man can be, ſo long as you doe not wrong me, iniure,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14604:31"/>diſgrace me, or take away my good name; but indeede if you abuſe me, or croſſe me of my will in any thing. Oh then you muſt pardon me, I am ſomewhat paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, I may not endure, or put vp ſuch abuſes, at any hand: No, may you not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure them? What then may you endure? Surely no more then a beare, a dog, a horſe, or a hog may. But it is the propertie of all thoſe that will be the Diſciples of our Lord and <hi>Sauiour Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, to forgiue,</hi> and forget with meekeneſſe, all iniuries and wrongs; they will not only be kinde to the kinde, and ſhew curteſie for curteſie, for this the verieſt repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and deepeſt diſſembler in the world may doe, <hi>but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14604:31"/>they will ouercome euill with goodneſſe,</hi> they wil ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the mercileſſe, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp many wronges and offences. And as they looke for pardon from God, for far greater offences; ſo will they not ſtick eaſily to giue pardon for theſe leſſer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. An excellent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be ſeene herein in <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whoſe brethren after the deceaſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> their father, fearing his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſubmitting them ſelues to him, he ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 50.19.</note> 
                        <hi>Feare not, for I alſo am vnder God.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, If I ſhould be ſo haſtie in reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my ſelfe vpon the wronges, which you haue offred me, may not God pay the ſame fourefold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine owne boſome?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14604:32"/>Plainly teaching euery true Chriſtian, ſo to behaue himſelfe towards offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors here in this life; as they would haue God to reward them hereafter.</p>
                     <p>If then you would haue forgiueneſſe at the hand of Almighty God, freely from your hearts, forgiue you your bretheren, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that you your ſelues are likewiſe vnder the ſame condemnation.</p>
                     <p>Now to forgiue, it is not enough to moderate the tongue, which is loues bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and interpreter, in not iudging euill of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; but alſo the ſimpathy and affection, of the heart is required (which is the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of loue) in forgiuing, to which Chriſt himſelfe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14604:32"/>annexeth a moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable promiſe; <hi>and it ſhall be for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you,</hi> becauſe we approue &amp; ſhew our ſelues thereby, to be the true children of God. Great is the equity of this precept, that we ſhould forgiue one another becauſe we are brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; But vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able is the mercy of God in promiſing vs forgiuenes. In forgiuing our brother, wee do no more then equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelfe requireth. <hi>Tu qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eum habes inimicum, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeum creatus eſt</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>). <hi>Deus vero eum quem creauit;</hi> thou haſt him to thine enemie, which was created with thee, but God hath him to his enemie, whom he created: thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueſt, when thou thy ſelfe needeſt forgiueneſſe; for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14604:33"/>who is he, that ſinneth not; but God who wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and cannot ſinne, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth thee.</p>
                     <p>And that euery good Chriſtian ſhould doe this, it is not onely meete, but for many reaſons neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, which ſhould be the rule and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for euery Chriſtian mans life.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> 
                        <hi>But I ſay vnto you, loue your enemies,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thy friend ſhould haue a ſeruant that ſhould great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſe and offend thee, and thou in thine anger ſhouldeſt riſe vp to ſtrike him, yet remembring that he is the ſeruant of thy deere friend thou wouldeſt bridle thy wrath, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14604:33"/>for thy friends ſake, to ſtrike him, leaſt thou ſhouldeſt offend, or looſe thy good friend.</p>
                     <p>This mildeneſſe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie God requireth at thine handes, that for his ſake, thou ſhouldeſt forgiue and ſpare thine enemie, his ſeruant, his creature, leaſt thou looſe his fauour, and friendſhip.</p>
                     <p>Somtimes we ſee a brother to ſpare a brother; leſt they ſhould diſpleaſe their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, <hi>Eſau</hi> a reprobate &amp; malicious man who bare a deadly hatred to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iacob</hi> could ſay,<note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> 
                        <hi>The daies of mourning for my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will come ſhortly, then will I ſtay my brother Iacob.</hi> He would not lay handes vpon his brother, while his father
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14604:34"/>leſt hee ſhould greeue and offend him; and ſhould not we much more refraine from hurting and ſeeking reuenge vpon our enemie, for the loue and reuerence we owe to our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whom wee are ſo many waies indebted, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Chriſt ſaying vnto vs, <hi>So ſhall my heauenly father doe vnto you,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> 
                        <hi>that is, deliuer you to the laylors, vntill you pay all that is due? Except yee forgiue from your hearts, each one to his brother their treſpaſſes. Ad tam magnum tonitru, quinon expergiſcitur, non dormit, ſed mortuus eſt;</hi> He that is not awaked at this ſo great thunder, is not a ſleepe, but is a dead man, ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If this can little moue thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14604:34"/>flinty heart, yet let theſe examples of heathen men preuaile ſomething with thee, of whom to be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and to come be-bind them in the practiſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, is not only a ſhame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtians, but ſhall alſo condemne them at the day of Iudgement.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phillip</hi> king of Macedon, being counſelled to puniſh one <hi>Archadius,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually railed vpon him when hee met; him, ſpake kindly vnto him, and ſent gifts vnto him, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards willed his friends to enquire what he ſaid of him among the <hi>Greekes:</hi> And when they anſwered, hee was become a great prayſer of the King; I am then (ſaid hee) a better <hi>Phiſitian</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14604:35"/>then any of you are.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hippocinus</hi> a noble man, conceiuing deepe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> by reaſon of ſome iniury done vnto his ſon. The next day early in the morning, <hi>Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biades</hi> came vnto his houſe, and being no ſooner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his dore, caſt off his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and offered his naked body, willing him to whip him at his pleaſure, as hee had worthily deſerued; At the ſight whereof <hi>Hippoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> by and by forgat the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, pardoned <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> and gaue him his daughter in mariage. If now theſe Ethnicks either through the moderation of their mindes, or humane wiſdom could willingly offer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, conſeſſe the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14604:35"/>iniury done, and forgiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued wronges; ſhall not they riſe vp in Iudgement, and condemne vs, which are ſo deadly in our malice, ſo obdurate in reuenge, ſo refractary, and ſtubborne in forgiuing wronges, that many thinke it vnpoſſible to frame their ſtony harts to be reconciled to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
                     <p>Firſt the duty we owe to our Chriſtian brother (if we be Chriſtians indeede) ſhould worke this effect in vs, that by our lenty and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, we may reforme and amend our neighbour.</p>
                     <p>Hereof the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. Pro. 15.</note> 
                        <hi>Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come euillwith goodnes,</hi> And <hi>Solomon A ſoft unſwer putteth away wrath, but grieuous words ſtirre vp anger.</hi> For euen as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14604:36"/>fire (the fuell being taken away) goeth out; ſo wrath and diſpleaſure is mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by mildneſſe; and as ſmoake ſo annoyeth the ſight, that a man cannot ſee what lieth, before him; ſo enuie and malice caſteth ſuch a cloud before reaſon; that one cannot eaſily iudge, or cenſure, rightly of the actions of his brethren, nor wherein wee our ſelues are delinquent.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, becauſe we are bound by charity, not to hurt our neighbour, for by reuenge and retorting euill for euill, we doe not onely proue our ſelues to be euill, but alſo miniſter occaſion of further fury, and pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation to our brother: What is this elſe, but <hi>Oleum
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14604:36"/>Camino addere?</hi> according to the prouerbe, to caſt oylein to the fire.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by many taunts and reproaches of an enemy, anſwered; I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with thee in this kind of combate. <hi>In quo qui vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur ipſo victore melior eſt,</hi> in which hee that is vanqi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, is the better man.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, wee ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and patientiy ſuffer wrong, for the edification of our neighbour, that wee may giue him an example of godlineſſe.</p>
                     <p>For as euery example of vertue, ſo eſpecially of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing iniuries, doth edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our neighbour, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force him to admire and loue vs, yea, though he be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14604:37"/>moſt vile, and wicked.</p>
                     <p>If the commandement of God as obedient children, cannot pierce our Adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine hearts; neither the loue, we owe vnto our brethren, as fellow members of one body; yet let the vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and profit, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to our ſelues thereby, as meere naturall men, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ſomewhat with vs, in this precept of forgiuing.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, leaſt thou hurt thy ſelfe, becauſe thou canſt not wreake thy reuenge vpon thine enemy, but thou muſt doe thy ſelfe a ſarre greater hurt. For if a man, for the diſliking that hee hath of a garment, which he weareth, that he might cut and teare it, ſhould thruſt the knife into his owne
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14604:37"/>bowells, were he not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be condemned of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame madneſſe? So thou canſtnot ſtirike thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but thou muſt giue thy ſelfe a more greenous wound; thou offendeſt God, pierceſt thine owne ſoule, through thine impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency, and pleafeſt thine aduerſary. Knoweſt thou not what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Whoſoeuer hateth his Brother,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> 
                        <hi>is a manſlayer, and yee know, that no manſlayer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paſſus es Malum?</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> haſt thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered wrong? <hi>Ignoſce, ne duo mali ſitis.</hi> Forgiue, that yee be not both wicked, If thou hateſt thy brother, thou hurteſt thine owne ſoule; If thou forgiueſt him, thou doſt good to thy ſelfe, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14604:38"/>thine enemy remaineth in his owne ſinne. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter madnes can there be, then to perſecute thine ene- with deadly hatred, ſeeing it cannot be without offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring great iniury to thine owne ſoule?</p>
                     <p>Is there any man ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, that if in eating, hee biteth his tongue with his teeth he will therefore pull out his teeth? Or if in clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a blocke, hee hurteth his foote, will hee to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged, cut off his arme? wouldeſt thou not iudge ſuch a one, to be out of his wits? Know then, that thy neighbour is neerer vnto thee, then thy teeth in thy head, or thine arme on thy body. Is it then the part of a wiſe man, to take reuenge
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14604:38"/>on his neighbour for a little iniury and reproch done vnto him, and ſo cut off and deſtroy the fellow member of the ſame body?</p>
                     <p>Surely, if there were no other reaſon, but this, to moue vs to condonation, and loue of our enemies, leſt wee moſt of all hurt our ſelues, ſeeing nature her ſelfe hath ingrafted in euery mans hart, to wiſh well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe, this ſhould be a ſufficient motiue vnto vs, to draw loue and kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our enemies. Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence knoweth how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert iniuries and reproches into gould, ſiluer, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones, euen as the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander</hi> is nouriſhed in the fire of tribulation, and as the fea fiſh is ſed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14604:39"/>with ſalt and bitter waters.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Socrates,</hi> when going in the ſtreete, one malepertly kicked him with his heele, and many maruelling that he ſo patiently put it vp, what ſhould I doe, (quoth he to them that perſwaded him to take the law vpon him,) <hi>Si quis aſinus me calce percuſſit, diceretus mihi voca eum in jus?</hi> If any Aſſe ſhould ſtrike me with his heele, would you wiſh me to goe to law with him?</p>
                     <p>Secondly, wee ſhould loue and forgiue an enemy, for the great profit, and good an enemy cauſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, And by experience we ſee, the very brute, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage beaſts, to be louing to their benefactours. If then reaſon it ſelfe enforceth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14604:39"/>from vs loue to a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, by the ſame law of reaſon wee are bound to loue our enemies, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times are more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and profitable to vs then a friend. Our friends many times doe winke at our infirmities, ſooth vs vp in our follies, ſuffer vs to runne on in our wickednes; but our enemy, which is ſharpe ſighted to prie into our life, maketh vs to walke warily and to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in our ſayings and doings, that wee giue him no occaſion to backbite, and diſcredit vs.</p>
                     <p>It was a wiſe ſaying of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that euery man needeth a true friend, or a watchfull enemy. For a friend (if hee be indeed a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14604:40"/>true friend) will euer tell vs the trueth and counſell vs for our good.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe often times we will not hearken vnto a friend, God ſendeth vs ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to counſell and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs in that, which our friends either will not, or dare not. And therefore one calleth an enemie, <hi>Optimum vita noſtrae Padagogum,</hi> the beſt Schoolemaſter of our life: <hi>Et medicum gratuitum ae ſalutarem;</hi> and a health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Phiſitian,</hi> which giueth his phiſicke freely, which if he doe but touch our vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and offences, cauſeth vs to amend them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedon,</hi> was wont to ſay, that hee was much behoulding vnto them of <hi>Athens,</hi> for that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14604:40"/>they ſpake euill of him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſaith he) I am made the better man whiles I endeuour <hi>et verbis, et factis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es mendaciſs conuincere,</hi> both by words, and deeds, to proue them lyers. Euen as thoſe that ſuſpect a diſeaſe, are carefully carefull, that they hurt not their crazed bodies by euill diet; ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, are an occaſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, of circumſpection in our liues and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28</note> 
                        <hi>For we know</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that all things worke together for the beſt, vnto them that loue God:</hi> So that a good man receiueth not a wound by the dart of his enemy, but an wholeſome plaiſter, to cure the rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of his ſoule, and to the furtherance of a godly life.</p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14604:41"/>
                     <p>Thirdly, wee ſhould bee prone and ready to for giue, becauſe we can not poſſibly haue peace with God, as long as we be at iarre with our Neighbours; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the neceſſity of it, ſhould moue vs to forgiue and loue our enemy. <hi>If yee bite and denoure one another,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> 
                        <hi>take heede yee be not conſumed one of another,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We ſee in an army, that the enemy hath neuer ſo great aduantage, as when the Captaine and Souldiers are at diſcord and ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues; but the whole life of a Chriſtian, what is it but a warfare vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth? And if then wee retaine peace with God, and our Neighbours, wee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14604:41"/>need not feare our enemies. But therefore wee are vanquiſhed of them, becauſe we haue little care of this peace amongſt our ſelues. This ineſtimable treaſure Chriſt left with his true members,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.27.</note> 
                        <hi>My peace I giue vnto you, my peace I leaue with you, not as the world gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, giue I vnto you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This peace of the world, is the conſent of wicked men amongſt themſelues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and good men, rather to be called a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, then a pacification; as <hi>Herod</hi> againſt <hi>Pilate, Pilate</hi> againſt <hi>Herod yet both agreed to put Chriſt to death. All the Sonnes of Iacob conſpiring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ioſeph, were friends in wickedneſſe,</hi> and held ſuch firme concord together,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14604:42"/>that for many yeers, though they diſſented among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, (as it commeth often to paſſe) yet they neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed to their Father, the ſelling of their Innocent Brother. But this is not the peace of Chriſt, which ſo maketh both one, that wee cannot haue peace with God, vnleſſe we hold peace with our brethren; neither can bee at peace with our brethren, except wee bee at peace with God firſt.</p>
                     <p>We are all conioyued in God, the beginning and author of all things, we all receiued our beginning of him, and therefore wee are bretheren and neighbours. And for this cauſe (as ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) He crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man but one and ſingle,<note place="margin">De ciuit. Dei.</note>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14604:42"/>that by this meanes, hee might commend vnto vs the vnity of ſociety, and bond of concord. If men not only be knit together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, by the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of nature, but alſo by the affection of cognati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that no man may fall away from the loue of God, but hee looſeth the loue of his Neighbor alſo, or can put off the loue of his Neighbour, but with all he looſeth the loue of God, and ſo it followeth, that if we bee not at peace among our ſelues, wee haue no peace with God: &amp; if we haue no peace with God, we can neither pray, nor per form any duty of godlines: therefore ſaith our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.</note> 
                        <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14604:43"/>Altar &amp; there reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leaue there thine offering before the Altar, and goe thy way: Firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy guift.</hi> And againe, when hee taught them to pray, he added,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.14.</note> 
                        <hi>For if yee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue men their treſpaſſes, your heauenly Father will alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue you; But if yee doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue men their treſpaſſes, no more will your Father forgiue you your treſpaſſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>God will not accept any ſeruice at our hands, except we be firſt reconciled to our brethren, becauſe there is no peace betweene vs and him, as long as there is no Chriſtian amity betweene vs and our Neighbours.</p>
                     <p>With what face can wee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14604:43"/>ſay the Lords Prayer; with what conſcience can wee craue forgiueneſſe of our heauenly Father, of our ten <hi>Thouſand Talents,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite ſinnes againſt his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty, <hi>when wee will not forgiue our Brother an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pence:</hi> That is, a treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of no moment, in compariſon of our gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes dayly againſt God. Is not this the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which wee make with God, <hi>As wee forgiue them which treſpaſſe againſt vs.</hi> O foole ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſttine,</hi> thou prayeſt againſt thy ſelfe, is it not as if thou hadſt ſaid. <hi>Lord forgiue mee not, ſeale faſt my ſinnes, forgiue me, as I forgiue others: but thou knoweſt, that I will not forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt me,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14604:44"/>therefore, O Lord, forgiue mee not?</hi> And thus through thy hard heartednes, thou prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not for thy ſelfe, but bringeſt a curſe vpon thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, another mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue which ſhould mooue vs to forgiue, is becauſe our enemy is worthy rather of commiſeration, then reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and reuenge.</p>
                     <p>But to meete now with the vſuall obiection of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men; <hi>How can I</hi> (they will ſay) <hi>refraine from ſeeking reuenge againſt him, who with his virulent tongue, hath impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my good name, who wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie calleth me into the Law, which ledeth mee with many contumelies, and neuer ceaſeth to reproach me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I am not ſo eſtranged from
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14604:44"/>the common ſence of men, but I thinke this to bee a grieuous diſeaſe among many. Let vs learne now how to cure this feſtered wound; weigh firſt the loſſe on either ſide, whether I pray thee doth thine enemy hurt moſt himſelfe or thee? He looſeth Gods fauour and friendſhip, in vſing thee ſo iniuriouſly; in reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee, he reproacheth God himſelfe, and in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he betrayeth his ſoule vnto eternall torments, and looſeth (without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) thoſe eternall ioyes, <hi>Which the eie hath not ſeene,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2, 9.</note> 
                        <hi>the eare hath not heard; neither hath entred into the heart of man, which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> Hee hath obſcured thy good
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14604:45"/>name, but he hath betrayed his owne ſoule; he hath but rent thy garment, but hee hath wounded his owne heart; he hath taken ſcarce a haire from thee, but hee hath bereft himſelfe of an eie: This being ſo, if there bee in thee the bowels of charity, ſhouldeſt thou not rather take pitty vpon thine enemy, which hath ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe, then greately to bee mooued, in that hee hath done thee a little iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? This the Holy Prophet ſignifieth when bee ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſ. 113 11.</note> 
                        <hi>They came about me like bees, but they were quenched euen as a fire among thornes.</hi> The <hi>Bee</hi> ſtingeth thy finger, but pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out his owne bowels, <hi>Animaſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in vulnere ponunt;</hi> They kill themſelues with
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14604:45"/>their ſtinging, and thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyeſt the hony: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou wouldeſt enioy the hony of heauenly glory, it is needfull that thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution of theſe waſpiſh enemies, where as the reuengerneuer wanteth a re-action on himſelfe, whileſt he ſeeks vengeance on man, findes vengeance of God, whileſt he ſhooteth the ſting of reuenge, he emp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tieth himſelfe <hi>of the bowels of mercy,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Col. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>kindneſſe humility, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phocion</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> two Noble men of <hi>Athens,</hi> the one being condemned to exile, the other to death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily: <hi>Ariſtides</hi> going in to exile, prayed that all things might ſucceede ſo happy and proſperous with the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14604:46"/>might neuer hereafter haue neede to remember <hi>Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Phocion</hi> being about to drinke the poyſoned <hi>Potion,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> wherewith hee ſhould die, charged his ſonne that hee ſhould neuer reuenge his vniuſt death vpon the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thraſibulus</hi> that Noble Citizen of <hi>Athens,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Val max.</note> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the thirty <hi>Spartan Tyrants,</hi> &amp; by this meanes, reſtored the former free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his Country, hee cauſed the law of perpetual obliuion of former iniuries to bee enacted, which they called <hi>(Legem obliuionis)</hi> the law of forgetfulneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Let Chriſtians then be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, not to aſpire vnto that perfection heerein,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14604:46"/>which many wiſe <hi>Heathens</hi> haue attained vnto. How far this brotherly forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is to be extended, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> himſelfe ſheweth in the parable of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruant,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 18.35</note> 
                        <hi>which owed ten thouſand Talents,</hi> concluding in theſe words: <hi>So likewiſe ſhall my heauenly Father doe vnto you, except you forgiue from your hearts, each one to his brother their treſpaſſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In theſe words, firſt wee are taught to whom this precept of forgiuing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries pertaineth. None are exempted which profeſſe to be Chriſts Diſciples: for he ſaith; <hi>Except yee forgiue each one,</hi> that is, of what degree, ſtate or condition ſoeuer he be of, rich or poore, Noble or Ignoble; King, or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14604:47"/>we are all ſinners, and doe pray daily: <hi>Forgiue vs our debts, as wee forgiue our debtors.</hi> Let the proud ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this, which being puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with the confidence of their birth or dignities, thinke that they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſpiſe, wrong, and tread vnder foot, the ſimple obſcure, and poore man.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, hee ſheweth whom hee ſhould forgiue, <hi>His brother:</hi> He might haue ſaid, his follow ſeruant: but hee would haue vs to lift vp our eyes higher, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that all men are not onely of the ſame conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as ſeruants; but alſo of the ſame nature and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as the Sonnes of God; who was ſo farre from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the baſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14604:47"/>that hee would haue his onely begotten Sonne to bee contemptible and poore, that he might make vs rich.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, hee teacheth what wee ſhould forgiue, <hi>Their treſpaſſes.</hi> He ſpeaketh indefinitely, that hee might comprehende all things wherewith our neighbour hath offended vs: for how great ſoeuer is the iniury done vnto vs, it may in no ſort be compared vnto that wherein wee haue offended God.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, hee expreſſeth the meaſure and manner of forgiuing, ſaying; <hi>From your hearts:</hi> that is, not in naked words, with an hypocritical and diſſembling heart, but truly and ſeriouſly, that not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14604:48"/>ſo much as a ſparkle of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, hatred, or rank or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine behind in our hearts: which particle, reproueth their contumacy, <hi>Which ſay, they will forgiue, but withall proteſt, they cannot forget the iniury, neither can they endure the ſight of ſuch as haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe forgiue not from their hearts, but in words onely; nay, not ſo much as in words, ſeeing they fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in their hearts the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory thereof, and doe not conceale it.</p>
                     <p>Wee ſhould in forgiuing of iniuries, imitate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſo forgiueth our iniquities, that hee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth them no more: for if our ſinnes were ſtill in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14604:48"/>with God, how could the hope of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation be firme and certain vnto vs? And therefore the Princely Prophet prayeth, <hi>That God would not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the ſinnes of his youth.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7.</note> And that which neceſſity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth vs to craue at the hands of God, is it not meet that wee ſhould ſhew the ſame to our brethren? Wee would not that God ſhould remember our ſinnes, and ſhall wee keepe in memory old grudges and offences of our brethren and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? Surely ſuch make themſelues vnworthy of the mercies of God; <hi>Being deſtitute of faith, working by loue.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moſt memorable, and neuer to be forgotten, was
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14604:49"/>the dealing of the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Abraham,</hi> with his nephew <hi>Lot,</hi> when Sathan aſſaied to kindle contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their quarrelling ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; <hi>Abraham</hi> being eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie way the better man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Vncle, and his elder, <hi>Who already had ſeene the day of Chriſt;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn 8.56.</note> had alſo learned the leſſon of humility of Chriſt; hee ſtood not vpon his <hi>Summu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ius,</hi> his right &amp; reputation, but came firſt to <hi>Lot,</hi> and was the profferer of peace, ſaying;<note place="margin">Gen. 13.8.</note> 
                        <hi>I pray thee let there bee no ſtrife betweene me and thee, and betweene my heardmen and thine, and why? for wee are brethren:</hi> Hee ſought peace <hi>Concedendo de ſuo Iure,</hi> By yeelding of his right. Now there are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14604:49"/>to bee found (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) which will not yeeld one foote of their right for brotherly vnities ſake: this proffer of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> is counted but folly now yea of thoſe which yet would be eſteemed his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, this benefit alſo we make through patience towards an enemy, (which is not the leaſt) that being accuſtomed to deale iuſtly and friendly with an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, wee ſhall the better frame our ſelues to liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciably and kindly with our familiar friends, and to doe nothing fraudulently, and deceitfully in friendſhip. Let vs therefore I beſeech you, caſt out of our minds the remembrance of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14604:50"/>which is the very wood and fuell to nouriſh reuenge, and which exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth our harts againſt our brethren.<note place="margin">Col. 3.12.</note> 
                        <hi>Let vs, as the Elect of God, put vpon vs tender mercy, kindneſſe, long ſuffering, forbearing one another, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing one another, as Chriſt for gaue you, euen ſo doe ye.</hi> Let this ſweet promiſe of our Sauiour: <hi>And ye ſhall be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen;</hi> quench in vs all rancor and malice, and ouerſway in our thoughts all reaſons of fleſh &amp; bloud, which ſeeke to moue vs to reuenge: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that in no other Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Lords Prayer we ſo pray, as to indent with God, but in this onely: <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs, as wee forgiue others.</hi> In which couenant with God, if wee bee found liars,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14604:50"/>we pray in vaine, our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are againſt our ſelues; ſeeing our ſinnes are not forgiuen, becauſe wee are not truly inſerted in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> vnleſſe we forgiue one anther; except wee manifeſt our faith, in loue towards our neighbor: Forgiue (ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) leſt whiles thou denie mercy to thy brother, thou ſhut the mercy of thy Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father from thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note> 
                        <hi>For there ſhall bee iudgement mercileſſe, to him that ſheweth no mercy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But if all this cannot ſuppreſſe the rage of thy wreakefull humour, but thou muſt needes ſeeke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge: I will permit thee to be carried with the current of thy paſſions, vpon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14604:51"/>that thou wilt bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with him that indeede hath done thee that iniury: And who is hee? verily (as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith) euen hee which ruleth in thine enemies heart, the Diuell I meane, which inflameth him with the firebrands of wrath and armeth him with his ſpirit againſt thee; it is hee that vſeth thine enemies hand as a Sword, to ſtrike thee, and his tongue as an arrow to ſhoote at thee. If an horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould ſtrike thee with his ſpeare, wouldeſt thou bee angry with his horſe? So, if thou bee hurt by thine enemy, ſeek e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>euenge againſt the Diuell, which is his rider; hee is the author of the wrong the wretched man is but the diuels inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14604:51"/>wherewith he ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thee: why then doeſt thou boile in hatred againſt the man, letting the Diuell alone, who indeede is the Author of the wrong? what is this elſe, but to imitate the dog, which ſnarleth and biteth at the ſtaffe or ſtone wherewith hee is ſtruken, and leaueth the man which caſt them. Let vs therefore leaue off to purſue our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with hatred and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, and bend our force againſt the Diuell, the true Author of all euill, and hold perpetuall warre with him.</p>
                     <p>If this reaſon doe little moue thee, lift vp thine eies vnto God, who permitteth this iniury to bee done to thee for the good of thy ſoule. So when <hi>Dauid</hi> fled
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14604:52"/>from the wrath of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and was thus deſpightfully curſed, &amp; railed on by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Shimei;</hi> and when one of his men of warre asked leaue of the King, <hi>To take the head from this raylers ſhoulders;</hi> this holy man was ſo farre from reuenge, that he anſwered:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.16.</note> 
                        <hi>Let him alone, for the Lord hath bidden him to curſe Dauid, who dare then ſay, wherefore haſt thou done ſo?</hi> And afterward, <hi>Suffer him, for the Lord hath bidden him to curſe: It may bee the Lord will looke vpon mine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and doe mee good for his curſe this day.</hi> Here ye ſee this good King aſcribed this reproach, not ſo much vnto his enemy that did it, as vnto God that permitted it: which holy <hi>Iob</hi> alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14604:52"/>imputing the loſſe of his goods not vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, which was but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument thereof, but vnto God, ſaying;<note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>The Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and the Lord taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But thou wilt ſay againe; <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>
                        </label> My enemy hath not taken from me my riches, but my honour, good name, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reputation, the which (as ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) is dearer to euery good man then any riches.</p>
                     <p>I anſwere,<note place="margin">Solution.</note> thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued man, thou art decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; not hee that receiueth the iniury, but he that doth the imury, looſeth his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: For euen as the man that is bountifull, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to his neighbour doth not ſo much increaſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14604:53"/>his neighbours praiſe, as his owne. So he that doth iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto another man, not ſo much diminiſheth his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, whom he reproacheth, as he impayreth his owne honour, in ſhewing himſelfe a malicious railer, or back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmed that man to be like vnto <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſonne of God, which pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſuffereth iniury; and him to be like <hi>Iudas</hi> the trai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour, that doth the iniury. See, ſee, how farre different the iudgement of this holy man is, from the common opinion of the world now a daies. Seeing therefore, as good Children, it is our eſpeciall glory, to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our father, let vs alſo in pardoning iniuries <hi>be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14604:53"/>as our heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y father is mercifull.</hi> Thus much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fourth work of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſoule, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this word <hi>Remitte.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Fer.</head>
                     <p>THe fift worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy to the ſoule, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et forth in bearing with the weake, This duty S. <hi>Paul</hi> enioyneth, ſaying;<note place="margin">Galat. 6.2.</note> 
                        <hi>Beare ye one anothers burthen, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.23 24.</note> 
                        <hi>Giue not thine heart to all the words men ſpeake, leſt thou heare thy ſeruant curſing thee, for oft times thy heart knoweth, that thou likewiſe thy ſelfe haſt curſed others. Antigonus</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring certaine ſouldiers rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon him hard by his tent, who thought that hee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14604:54"/>was not ſo neere, diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe vnto them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Can ye not goe further to ſpeake ill of me?</hi> So far was he, from reuenging their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen reuilings, that he onely deſired them, to raile out of his hearing. That we may therefore the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this duty, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue all things in the beſt part, let vs take things in the beſt ſence, and meaning. Let vs, I ſay, ſo iudge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as wee would wiſh; they ſhould iudge of vs. Let vs not be ſo ſuſpicious, and miſdeeming, as (for the moſt part) many men be. For this ill conſtruction, and wrong interpretation, of things, by haling and wreſting them, to the worſt ſence and meaning, is the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14604:54"/>way to fill our hearts full of bitternes, and to make vs ready, vpon euery light oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to fall to brangling, brawling, and contention with our brethren. When one ſhall haue theſe doubts perhaps hee thinks thus of me, it may be hee had this meaning, or did it to this intent, or the like, theſe or the like conceits, will very maruelouſly infect the hart with the leauen of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckoneth it as a chiefe note of an ill man, and a ſure brand of a wicked perſon, <hi>To take all things in the worſt parte.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 1.29.</note> But a courteous and meeke man will be ſure, if a thing may be expounded one way, better then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to take it in the beſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14604:55"/>ſence, and to make the beſt of it.</p>
                     <p>Our Lord and maſter <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> was ſo farre from taking his bitter paſſion, in the worſt ſence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that in the middeſt thereof, hee prayed ſaying; <hi>Father forgiue them, they know not what they doe.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 23.34</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But foraſmuch as our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt</hi> condemneth raſh iudgement in the next verſe, ſaying, <hi>Iudge not, and yee ſhall not be iudged, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne not, and yee ſhall not be condemned:</hi> I purpoſe a little to touch this point, and ſo much the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe raſh cenſurers oppoſe themſelues by all meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this duty. This raſh iudgement is that which is gathered of ſome light con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14604:55"/>or ſignes. This iudgement the Scripture calleth iudgement accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, forbiden by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. <hi>Whereas he ſaith,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 7.24.</note> 
                        <hi>Iudge not according to the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, but iudge righteous iudgement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There be ſixe markes, whereby this Iudgement according to the outward appearance may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                     <p>Firſt hee which looketh onely on the outward fact, without conſidering the cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumſtances thereof, which may alter the manner of the fact.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Without weighing the in tention of the dooer, which may be honeſt though hee erre in the fact 3. Without
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14604:56"/>weighing the end, for which it was done, which in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if it be good, may, at leaſt wiſe extenuate the fault, without po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering the cauſe, &amp; the originall of the act, as that it was done the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> row euill company, or by ſome ſtrong temptation or violence. 5. Without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration had of the time, place, or perſon, all which may either excuſe, or much leſſen an actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſeemeth euil. Laſtly he judgeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the appearance which what he diſliketh in one,<note place="margin">Iohn 7.23.</note> he approueth in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>As the Phariſes which al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed of circumciſion to be done on the Sabb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> day but were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with Chriſt, for making a man euery whitwhole on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day. The Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Leuit. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:14604:56"/>
                        <hi>concerning the triall of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, that the Leaper ſhould be ſhut vp ſeuen daies.</hi> Much leſſe would hee haue vs, which haue no authority, to iudge of Leapers, that is of the ſinnes of others, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily and raſhly to ſtep forth and cenſure the ſecret infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of others, which can not be ſo eaſily diſcerned as the Leproſie of the body.</p>
                     <p>This kinde of iudgement is opoſite to Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, which if we be Gods children, ſhould ſhine forth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, it ſpringeth from a two fould peſtilent roote.</p>
                     <p>Firſt becauſe a man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is wicked, hee iudgeth others to be like himſelfe; neither can any iudge bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of another, then he doth of himſelfe. <hi>Qualis quiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14604:57"/>et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>liot iudis at.</hi> As the man is, ſo he iudgeth of others. The coueteous man, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aconſtomed in buying and ſelling to deceiue, ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all others in the ſame. The Adulter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> and carnall liuer, eaſily miſdeemeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. So impure <hi>Nero,</hi> was perſwaded, <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> pudicum,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suttoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>) that no man liued honeſtly, <hi>Mala mens, mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> An euill conſcience hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer an euil ſurmiſing minde.</p>
                     <p>Secondly raſh iudgement proceedeth of hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed and euill will; for of him whom a man hateth, or enuieth, vpon the leaſt ſignes, hee is ready to iudge euill and condemne him. Euery one is eaſily perſwaded in the thing that he deſueth. <hi>Such
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14604:57"/>was Simon the Phariſes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon Chriſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 7.39.</note> 
                        <hi>for that hee ſuffered himſelfe to be touched of the ſinfull woman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This raſh iudgement is cauſed of the long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the manners of men, that when they haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> men fall into many ſinnes, they are in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereby, vpon very light occaſions or ſurmiſes, to condemne their brethren.</p>
                     <p>But it ſhould not ſo be, if wee be truly gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ted into <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> charity will meaſure all our thoughts and actions. <hi>Loue</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>thinketh not euill;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13 5</note> 
                        <hi>vnto the pure are all things pure,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> 
                        <hi>but vnto them that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, &amp; vnbeleeuing, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> nothing pure, but euen their mindes and conſciences are defiled.</hi> And
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14604:58"/>is euen as the ſwine which are euer rooting in dyre, &amp; dung; ſo an euill and filthy minde is alway plodding vpon filthy things; and hee that is affected with wicked deſires, loueth to be rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the ſame vpon another either that he might iuſtif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> his owne faults, by the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pariſon of other mens, or at the leſtwiſe, by reaſon of the multitude of offendours make his owne (through ſociety) ſeeme light. Euen as they that can finde little to doe at home, are often walking and gadding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade; ſo when men are negligent in examining their owne liues, they are curious in ſcanning and iudging, the dooings of others men. <hi>Non iudicat
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14604:58"/>perſonalitor, qui diligit aquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) in his thirtieth ſermon vpon <hi>Iohn.</hi> For we iudge according to the perſon, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the matter, becauſe wee are accepters of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and loue not the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of him, whom weiudge.</p>
                     <p>But ſhall I ſet thee downe a rule, whereby to examine thy iudgement, whether it proceede from reaſon, or from ſome corrupt paſſion? Before thou condemneſt thy brother, Imagine the fact which thou diſlikeſt, to be done by ſome other, whom thou loueſt, or transferre it vpon thy ſelfe, ſuppoſe thou thy ſelfe hadſt done it. And if the fact doth yet diſpleaſe thee, then it is reaſon, and not thy paſſion that iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14604:59"/>But if now thou canſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and brooke it without any diſtaſt well enough, or with <hi>Menius</hi> in the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t ſay, <hi>Egomet mihi igu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſco,</hi> I pardon my ſelfe, and count it no f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ult in thy ſelfe, ſurely thy iudgement is corrupt, ſome depraued affection hath deceiued thee: It is a law among the good Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to be coparme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> as well in their loſſe, as in their gaine; ſo ſhould it be in the ſociety of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. For euen as charity ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an others good her owne, and ſo gaineth much ſo mercy maketh alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers euill her owne, by a fellow feeling of others mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, according to this of the Apoſtle <hi>Reioyce with them that reioyce,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 12.16.</note> 
                        <hi>weepe, with
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14604:59"/>them that weepe, and be of like affection one towards another.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But on this iron and flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty age of the world; where are now become the bowels of mercy &amp; louing kindnes? This ſimpathy <hi>of affection one towards another,</hi> which was amongſt the Chriſtians of ancient time <hi>which were of one heart and one ſoule.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Acts. 4.</note> in what angle of the world (almoſt) ſhall we find them. Shall we locke them, as one once ſought for a good man, in the temples among the tombes of the dead? For ſurely ſuch is in theſe daies the depriuation of manners, from that which was in our fore-fathers daies, that we may truly ſay as the wiſe man did once, <hi>Quos fugiam ſcio, quos ſequar
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14604:60"/>non video,</hi> whom to beware of I know, but whom I ſhould follow I ſee not. Nothing in Chriſtian ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is worſe, or more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome then ſuch kind of vncharitable cenſurers of their neighbours; who as it were, violently divulge &amp; lay open mens ſecrets, pull from them the beſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their good name, and caſt out of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane mouths all the filth and corruptions of their brethren, that is, their faults and infirmities. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may the better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how we commit this odious ſinne, I will here ſet downe ſome remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this peruerſe and dangerous diſeaſe of raſh iudgement.</p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:14604:60"/>
                     <p>Firſt, if our neighbour haue done or ſaid any thing we ſhould not raſhly iudge or condemne it, interpret, calumniate, or touch his credit, for wee know not whether the report be true; ſometimes this, or that may be faſtned on a good man. It was a goulden counſaile of the wiſe man.<note place="margin">Ecleſicus 19.10.11.15.</note> 
                        <hi>If thou haſt heard a word againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Let it die with thee, and be ſure it will not burſt thee. A foole traueleth with a word as a woman with childe. Tell thy friend his fault, for often times a ſlander is raiſed, and giue no credit to euery word.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly though a thing be done or ſpoken (as wee thinke) amiſſe, yet we are ignorant of the cauſes and occaſions, why then doe we
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14604:61"/>exaggerate and iudge of things vnknowne. <hi>Good workes are manifeſt, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe that are otherwiſe cannot be hid;</hi> that is, a man may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times doe that which is good and right, but thou knoweſt not by and by his intent; yet afterwards thou maiſt find that he did well.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, conſider, that if thou hadſt bin in the place of thy neighbour at that time, thou wouldſt (perhaps) haue done, as he did. <hi>Digito courpeſce la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellum,</hi> Put thy finger to thy mouth;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> leſt thou be iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thy ſelf, <hi>Iudge nothing,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>before the time,</hi> And S. <hi>Iames</hi> willeth vs,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ames. 4.</note> 
                        <hi>not to ſpeake euill arte of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi> And againe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> giueth this
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14604:61"/>counſaile <hi>Let vs not Iudge one another any more,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.13.</note> 
                        <hi>but vſe our Iudgement rather in this, that no man put a ſtumbling blocke before his brother. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quils</hi> and <hi>Libels</hi> are not to be caſt forth, <hi>as the heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh manner of ſome is;</hi> for who appointed thee, a iudge of thy brother.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, if thou findeſt a defect in thy brother, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that vnder that defect many vertues may be hid, many good parts, as that of <hi>Cicero,</hi> in the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> anſwering one <hi>Memmius,</hi> who declaymed againſt <hi>Marcus Cato,</hi> becauſe hee made merry all night long: why (ſaid <hi>Cicero</hi>) didſt thou not adde alſo, <hi>Quodtota die aleas ludit, that hee plaid at dice alday. Cato</hi> hauing ſpent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14604:62"/>
                        <hi>the whole day in ſerious buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the common wealth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed himſelfe the more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally at night.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fiftly, to conſider that he which now hath grieuouſly falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to day, by Gods grace may be conuerted to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; for God is able to make him ſtand. If thou wilt needes iudge, <hi>Noſce teipſum.</hi> Begin firſt with thy ſelfe, and perchance thou ſhalt find thy ſelfe worſe then him, whom thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt. <hi>Iuſtus prius eſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſator ſui.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Take good heede, leſt in the ſame thing thou iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt another, thou condemneſt not thy ſelfe.</hi> Take heede I ſay that thou bee not ſtayned with the ſame crime, and ſo giue ſentence againſt thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">2 Sam 12.</note> 
                        <hi>The man that hath done
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14604:62"/>this, ſhall ſurely die</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> But what ſaid the Prophet? <hi>Thou art the man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conclude, if thou canſt not excuſe the action of thy neighbour, yet excuſe his intention, impute it to his ignorance, or that hee was ouercome with ſome grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temptation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with if another had beene aſſaulted, he might likewiſe haue yeelded. This the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> 
                        <hi>If a man be fallen by occaſion into any fault ye which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; conſidering thy ſelfe leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi> Surely if a man would looke into himſelfe, he ſhould find that hee hath enough to doe at home in the houſe of his owne conſcience, ſo that he
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14604:63"/>would find no time to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into other mens ſoules. But this age yeeldeth great ſtore of Phiſitians, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one will be launcing the carbuncles of others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, but they neuer haue care to cure their own Vlcers. Euery one would be an eye in the body of the Church, none a hand. Such without authority, vſurpe the office of the eye, but to be a hand in doing good few are willing. They are ready to carpe at other mens labours, when they put their hand to nothing that good is. But let vs firſt iudge our ſelues, and ſo we ſhall more charitably looke into the faults of others. <hi>Let vs I ſay bee mercifull as our heauenly father is mercifull.</hi>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:14604:63"/>Thus much touching raſh iudgement, and the fift worke of mercy to the Ioule deſcribed by this word <hi>Fer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>ORA.</head>
                     <p>THe ſixt &amp; laſt worke of mercy toward the ſoule conſiſteth in praying for all men, A duty ſo neceſſary, as without it, wee haue no meanes to expreſſe our wants to our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. S. <hi>Auſten</hi> calleth prayer <hi>Interprei defiderij,</hi> a key to valocke the ſecrets of our heauenly deſires; the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity whereof our bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> ſets forth, when hee taught his diſciples to pray, and alſo the benifit, when he ſaid, <hi>Aske and yee ſhall haue,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 7.7.</note> 
                        <hi>ſeeke and yee ſhall finde; knock and it ſhall be opened vnto you.</hi>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:14604:64"/>And he yeeldeth a reaſon in the next verſe, ſaying, <hi>For whoſoeuer, asketh receiueth he that ſeeketh, findeth, and to him that knocketh, it ſhall be opened.</hi> From hence may you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue, that oft times our wants and miſeries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from our coldneiſe and neglect of prayer. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſt men are greatly to be blamed for neglecting ſo religious and heauenly a duty. This was not the vſe of the holy Prophets and Patriarks.<note place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note> 
                        <hi>Daniell, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Kings decree to the contrary, vſually prayed three times a day.</hi> And we ought eſpecially in theſe daies to call to minde the admirable deuotion of the Sonne of God (deuotion waxing key-cold amongſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14604:64"/>men). Let vs therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our ſelues, and thinke a little more of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon God, by religious and deuoute prayer, remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bring who it was, that ſpent whole nights in prayer, when he was labouring for the ſinnes of the world, and the ſaluation of our ſoules. If the eyes of God doe at all times, and in all places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould vs, then moſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when wee preſent our ſelues before him in prayer; when both attention of minde, and humiliation of body co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curre, actions moſt befitting humble ſutors: we often repeate that of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.6.</note> 
                        <hi>O come, let vs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and fall downe, before the Lord our Maker;</hi> but we doe it not, by humbling our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14604:65"/>to ſue pardon for our ſoules. To approach &amp; enter into the place of prayer, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> if we came to ſit in commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, or would countenance him in his own houſe, is as an vnreuerent a cuſtome as heart can wiſh. To dehort men now a daies from long prayer, we are eaſed of that labour, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many care not how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they pray. Nay which is more, when ſome altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect this holy duty vnto God, wherein Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans aſſemble themſelues by publique prayer; as if by preaching, they would haue euermore God doe ſeruice vnto them, but they by prayer would neuer do ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto God. And yet for all this, not onely to ſpeake
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14604:65"/>of prayer, but of feruency in prayer, may further our Chriſtian deſires in Gods ſeruice, ſeeing our zeale is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo cold as we may ſeem rather to ſpeake, then pray, ſeeing the very of houſe pray or, is almoſt made nothing leſſe; whereas our repayring thither, puts vs in minde of a duty to be performed. He therefore that prayer not in the Church, doth as he that eates not at abanquet, that learnes not at the ſchoole, that fights not at the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, that walkes not when he is in his iourney.<note place="margin">Mat 26.31</note> Let vs obſerue Chriſts praying in the garden, <hi>when his ſoule began to be ſorrowfull,</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to moue vs to a duecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of prayer.</p>
                     <p>In this had prayer, we may
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14604:66"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe circumſtances; firſt, that it was ſolitary, for that hee now left his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as he had vſually done before, when he went out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to pray, &amp; this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto vs ſolitary pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly he prayed with humiliation of body.<note place="margin">Luk. 22.41 Mat. 26.39</note> S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſayth. <hi>He kneeled, and prayed; S. Mathew and S. Marke, that hee fell proſtrate vpon the earth.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mark 14.55.</note> The Euangeliſts may ſoone be reconciled; for it may ſeeme he firſt kneeled, and afterward for faintneſſe he was forced to fall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; and this commends to vs humiliation in prayer.<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.41.</note> 
                        <hi>When he raiſed Lazarus, and reſtored the dumbe man to the vſe of ſpeaking,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Marke 7.38.</note> 
                        <hi>we find he lifted vp his eyes to heauen;</hi> which was ſometimes his geſture
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14604:66"/>in prayer: when <hi>Moſes</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.12.</note> 
                        <hi>hee lifted up his hands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the going downe of the Sun:</hi> which houlding vp of his hands <hi>Dauid calleth his eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſa. 141.4. Acts 7.60.</note> When <hi>Steuen</hi> prayed, <hi>hekneeled down, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts example</hi> here in the ſecond place me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned.</p>
                     <p>The third circumſtance in this our <hi>Sauiours</hi> praying is, that it was iuſt and right; for he ſubiected his will, to the wil of his father, ſaying, <hi>Si iuvis.</hi> If thou wilt, which teacheth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelues, and all our petitions to the will of God.</p>
                     <p>The fourth, that it was with ſorrow; for hee was in an agony, and this putteth vs in minde of that of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26</note> 
                        <hi>The ſpirit helpeth our infirmities, for wee know not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14604:67"/>what to pray as wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>, but the ſpirit worketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> for vs, with ſighes which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The fift that it was with perſeuerance; for hee came three times vnto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, three times, and in three places was hee temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and three times did he here pray, and willed his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Mat 26.41.</note> 
                        <hi>To watch and pray that they enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Oh what deuotion was here, his laſt ſupper being ended, he goeth forth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and ſpeakes vnto them (as a louing father vpon his death-bed, when hee hath not much to ſay) giues his Children precepts at parting, which they ſhould
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14604:67"/>remember when he is gone from them, of which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, this was not the leſt, <hi>Watch and pray:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 26.41</note> 
                        <hi>that you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into temptation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſurely; wee haue no ſweeter incenſe, then our de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uotion offered vp by prayer, we haue no better Oratours to pleadeour cauſe, no ſurer Ambaſſadours, to conclude our peace, then our humble ſupplications to Almighty God, who healeth our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and forgiueth our ſinnes, who ſitteth euer in commiſſion, to heare our ſuits, and looketh, that wee ſhould ſend vp prayers, and petitions to him, that hee may alſo ſend downe his mercies, and graces to vs.</p>
                     <p>By which meanes, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a ſpirituall traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14604:68"/>with God himſelfe, we giue a cup of could wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and he returnes a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the waters of life to vs.</p>
                     <p>Wee giue him, with the poore widdowe two mites,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> 
                        <hi>and hee giues vs againe the whole treaſure of the temple.</hi> The mercy of God (ſaith one) is like a veſſell full to the very brim; if once his children, by the hand of faithfull prayer, beginne to take of it, it doth ouerflowe vnto them.</p>
                     <p>It is not with God, as with men, amongſt whom, thoſe who are petitioners, are wont to be troubleſome vnto him; but with God, the more we offer vp our praiers vnto him, the more wee are accepted of him. For with
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14604:68"/>him the gates of mercy are wide open to all poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that will make their prayers vnto him.</p>
                     <p>Come and welcome.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Hannah being barren, by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er obtained a ſonne; Elias,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 King. 18.</note> 
                        <hi>raine Eliſha a ſonne,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 King. 4</note> 
                        <hi>for the Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, which being dead, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his prayer reſtored to life.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Acts 9.20.</note> 
                        <hi>Peter by prayer raiſed Dorcas and Paul Eutichus, from death to life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is recorded in the life of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yong man, hauing by an indenture of couenants writen, and ſealed with his owne bloud, giuen his ſoule in reuerſion to the deuill, that the fiend was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, at the inſtant prayer of the ſaid <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to giue to the young
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14604:69"/>man his deed againe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ruſſinus</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo write, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Chriſtian Emperour, in a great battaile againſt <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> when he ſaw the huge multitude, that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againſt him, and ſo in the ſight of man, there was an apparent our throw at hand; he gets him vp into place eminent, in the ſight of all the army, fals downe proſtrate vpon the earth, be ſeecheth God, if euer hee would looke vpon a ſinfull creature, to helpe him, in this time of greateſt neede; ſuddenly there aroſe a mighty, winde, which blow the darts of the enemies backe vpon themſelues, in ſuch wonderfull manner, as <hi>Eugenius</hi> with all his hoaſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14604:69"/>was cleane diſcomfited.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed by ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, let vs ſometimes with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> 
                        <hi>leaue our terrene affaires, as he left his ſeruants beneath, when he want into the mount to ſacrifice to God:</hi> ſo in ſickneſſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, and in times of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, then ſhould wee fly vnto our ſureſt ſtay of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; then ſhould we aſcend into the contemplation of heauenly things, and haue recourſe to Gods mercy, as to a City of refuge,<note place="margin">Pſal 50.15</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> counſelleth: <hi>Demus operam, vt moriamur in precatione Call vpon me, in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee, &amp; thou ſhalt prayſe me. In the time of trouble;</hi> there is a refuge for extremitie.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14604:70"/>
                        <hi>And I will heare thee;</hi> there is a reward of <hi>mercy;</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt praiſe me;</hi> there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexe of a thankfull duty. <hi>Chriſt wils all,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 11.28</note> 
                        <hi>that are weary, and heauy Laden, to come vnto him,</hi> and they ſhall not looſe their labour, for he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh them. In time of neede no ſurer ſanctuary, then by humble prayer, to repayre to God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.2</note> 
                        <hi>Wherefore as the eies of ſeruants, looke vnto the hand of their maſter, and as the eies of a mayden vnto the hand of her miſereis;</hi> ſo let our eyes wayte vpon the Lord, our God, vntill hee haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
                     <p>But as prayer and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing is our Chriſtian ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, ſo muſt it agree with that of the Iſraelites, in ſixe points.</p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:14604:70"/>
                     <p n="1">1. As theirs was ſeaſoned with ſalt, ſo ours muſt be with the truth of a good conſcience.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. As theirs was brought to the prieſt, ſo ours muſt be preſented to God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As theirs was ſlaine; ſo when we pray, we muſt kill all our lewd, and malicious affections.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. As theirs was waſht with water, ours muſt bee with teares of repentance.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. As theirs was without blemiſh; ſo ours muſt be without hypocriſie.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, as theirs was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with fire, ſo ours muſt be with zeale.</p>
                     <p>And in this duty, we muſt imitate the bleſſed, <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr</hi> S. <hi>Steuen,</hi> who prayed for his enemies, ſaying, <hi>Lord
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14604:71"/>lay not this ſin to their charge:</hi> we muſt pray for all men.<note place="margin">Acts 7.</note> Thus much concerning the ſixe duties of mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſoule; <hi>Wherin let vs be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, as our heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:14604:71"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MISERICORS</hi> OR Motiues to Mercy.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part.</p>
                  <p>Comprehending all duties of mercy belonging to the Body.</p>
                  <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by IOHN BEALE 1619.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:14604:72"/>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:14604:72"/>
                     <head>The Argument.</head>
                     <p>HAuing (dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethren) fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the former treatiſe touching all the duties of mercy belonging to the ſoule. I now purpoſe by Gods bleſſed aſſiſtance, particularly to handle the workes of mercy due to the body, as they follow in this verſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viſito, Poto, Cibo, Redimo, Tego, Colligo, Condo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To viſit the ſicke, giue drinke to the thirſtie, bread to the hungry, to helpe the oppreſſed, to cloath the naked, to lodge the harbourleſſe to bury the dead.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:14604:73"/>
                     <head>Viſito</head>
                     <p>THe firſt duty of mercie to the body, conſiſteth, in viſiting, comforting and relieuing all thoſe, on whom God hath layd his heauy rod of ſickneſſe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, ſufficient hath beene deliuered in the third worke of mercie to the ſoule, touching ſpirituall conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſicke and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. It is the counſell of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews That we ſhould remember thoſe that are afflicted,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 13.3</note> 
                        <hi>as if we were alſo afflicted.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Be ye the members of one body.</hi> And members be all perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame paine and griefe: if any one, yea but the meaneſt, ſufferany thing the reſt are alſo pertakers
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14604:73"/>thereof. For whoſoeuer trippeth at the toe, his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, to bring the head to the ground. If therefore we haue the loue, that ought to be in the hearts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we cannot chuſe, but in ſome part, as hauing a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low feeling of the miſeries of our brethren, be ready to helpe them, and relieue them, and to doe workes of mercy toward them. And herein <hi>Iobs friends may be commended vntovs.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. 2.11.</note> It is ſaid that hauing heard of the miſery, wherin <hi>Iob</hi> was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly caſt, they came to him, not as the common cuſtome is, to bid him be of good cheere, and wee hope, you ſhall doe well, feare not, we will helpe you the beſt wee can &amp;c. <hi>but they came to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14604:74"/>with him, they wept with him, they rent their clothes, and ſat downe with him mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> they hearing their friends woe, would let him know, they were touched with it, and therefore they ſhew it by weeping, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and lamenting in the duſt, making his cauſe theirs, ſo neere as might be. And ſurely hee that is throughly and ſenſibly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with other mens mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, will be very ready and willing to relieue them, and to doe workes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to them. But for want of this partaking of other mens griefes, it commeth to paſſe, that men be ſo hardly drawne and haled to any worke of mercy; that it muſt be pulled from them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14604:74"/>by maine ſtrength, yea by many forcible arguments, reaſons; and inducements muſt they be conſtrained to it, before they will yeelde there vnto and when all is done, they beſtow a thing of no valew, nothing to the purpoſe yea, they that are bountifull enough, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of luſt and vanity, in playes, vaine ſhewes, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, wantonneſſe, and the like, are ſo ſparing in works of merey, that one can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wring a penny from them, by all the perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he can make. But why ſhould they be ſo ſlow, and vnwilling? Surely, becauſe they neither haue, nor will haue any ſenſe of other mens griefes, but put away al conſideration and regard of theſe things, and giue
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14604:75"/>themſelues wholly to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. In thoſe matters, which will coſt them many teares much lamentation, &amp; great griefe of hart, &amp; bring them no good hereafter, but much ſorrow, they care not how farre they run, and what charges, and expences they be at; but for viſiting the ſicke, duties of compaſſion, and workes of mercy, ſuch as will further their ſoules, and doe good to the church and Saints of God, they come off ſo ſlowly &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily, as though all were loſt, that were that way beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And thus it falleth out, becauſe their heartes are mercileſſe, and voide of compaſſion.</p>
                     <p>Whereas affliction ſhould makes v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> more mexciful, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14604:75"/>and compaſſionate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, as hauing our ſelues endured the like croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and miſeries, and our hearts, which are hard in themſelues, ſhould be ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and made the more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and in fellow feeling of their griefes, more ready and willing to yeeld vnto them any comfort, &amp; refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing.</p>
                     <p>Thus thoſe who haue beene ſicke, are apt to pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thoſe moſt, whom they ſee payned with the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; Thoſe who haue bin impriſoned, do more readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compaſſionate and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly helpe, and relieue thoſe, who are reſtrayned. Thoſe which haue beene pinched with penury, and paine with hunger, doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:14604:76"/>others pitty them, who being poore, want foode to feede them, and clothes to couer them.</p>
                     <p>Now therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clud this point, in as much as in this life, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing certaine; it being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten incident for men to flouriſh in a moment, and on a ſudden to be plunged into the pit of miſerable pouerty, or a affliction. Neither is there any man, that would refuſe comfort, when occaſion &amp; neceſſitie doth require it: why then ſhould wee with-hold that from our brethren, which wee ſhould expect at their hands towards our ſclues, if neede were. <hi>Let vs therefore be merifull towards others,</hi> as we would expect the mercy
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:14604:76"/>of God toward our ſelues; And thus much touching the firſt worke of mercy to the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Poto Cibo</head>
                     <p>THe Second and third worke of mercy to the body, conſiſts in giuing bread and drinke and other foode, to ſuch as want it. Theſe two, are as twins, which may not be parted; touching which duty S.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.20.</note> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If thine enemy hunger, feede him, If he thirſt, giue him drinke.</hi> If thine enemy, much more thy friend, yet ſuch is the hard hartedneſſe of the age and time wherein wee liue, that charity is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to a friend, nay ſcarce to a brother; how then ſhall an enemy expect
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14604:77"/>any fauour. Neuertheleſſe the ſpirit of God reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, by the mouth of <hi>Salo mon. To caſt our bread vpon the waters,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccle. 11.1 2.3.4.</note> 
                        <hi>for after many dayes we ſhall finde it. Giue a portion to</hi> 7, <hi>and alſo to</hi> 8. <hi>for thou knoweſt not what euill ſhall be vpon the earth.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, be liberall to the poore, for though it ſeeme to be as a thing ventred on the ſea, yet it ſhall bring thee profit. <hi>If the cloudes bee full, they will poure forth raine vpon the earth.</hi> As the clouds ſo the rich that haueal, oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, ſhould diſtribute li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally: <hi>If the tree fall toward the South, or toward the North in the place that it falleth, there it ſhal be.</hi> Be beneficiall there fore whileſt you liue, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life, there is no power.</p>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:14604:77"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He that obſerueth the winde ſhall not ſow, and hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the clouds, ſhall not reape.</hi> So he that feareth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, when neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty requireth, ſhall neuer doe his duty.</p>
                     <p>And thus you ſee <hi>Salomon</hi> in this <hi>Metaphoricall</hi> ſpeech ſtirreth vp the people of God, to the workeof mercy &amp; liberality towards ſuch as are with miſery and want afflicted. What we ſhould giue, he ſheweth, when hee ſaith <hi>(Caſt thy bread)</hi> by which word <hi>bread,</hi> he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth all kinde of foode, and meate for the preſeruation of the life of man, or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the reliefe, &amp; ſuſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our needy, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed brethren.</p>
                     <p>We are bound therefore
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14604:78"/>to giue whatſoeuer is requi ſit, to ſupply the want of ſuch as are in neede &amp; neceſſity.</p>
                     <p>There is alſo an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> to be obſerued in this word <hi>(Caſt:)</hi> the latine word <hi>Mitte,</hi> ſignifieth to ſend any thing, as if the almes; wee giue to the poore, were ſent by them into heauen. So it is reported of <hi>Laurence</hi> the <hi>Martir,</hi> who hauing diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore, the treaſures which <hi>Sextus</hi> left him, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe red <hi>Decius</hi> the Emperour, in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. <hi>The treaſure of the Church, which thou requireſt, In celeſtes The ſauros manus pau peru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deportauerunt,</hi> the hands of the poore haue carried them into the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury. If we will then lay vp our corne our garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; our money in a ſafe place, where
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14604:78"/>the the eues ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſteale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the mothes cate, nor the ruſt conſume them, letys ſend them to heauen by the hands of the poore, where weſhall be fure to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſafe kept &amp; that which we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with vs, if we giue to the poore, wee haue ſent it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs. Let vs then by the hands of the poore tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſport ſome partof our goods into heauen, &amp; commit it to the ſafe keeping of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will reſtore it, to our euerlaſting comfort.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, hee ſheweth what wee muſt giue, when he ſaith <hi>(Thy bread)</hi> of our owne not of that, which by right appertaineth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which we haue gotten bydeceit, and vniuſtmeanes,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14604:79"/>&amp; therefore he ſaith againe,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.9.</note> 
                        <hi>Honour God of thine owne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that is of that,</hi> which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> iuſtly and honeſtly gotten. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>A. hab, How hee lay vpon his hod, and would eate no bread,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">3 King 21.4.</note> ſaith <hi>Thoſerich Cormorants, may be ſaid rather to eate the bread of others, then their owne, which liue by catching, and oppreſſion, and mayntaine their expence, by rapine:</hi> and this <hi>Chryſoſtom noteth</hi> (in his thirteenth <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie</hi> vpon the firſt to the <hi>Corinths</hi> and the thirteenth) to be more ſhamefull, then for the poore to beg; for the poore craue of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort, and ſuch as willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue, that is of rich men, but the rich take it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, againſt their wills, and that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ragged &amp; baſe poore
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14604:79"/>they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues wearing clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of ſilke. And the Lord ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſa. 61.8.</note> 
                        <hi>that he hateth robbery as burnt offering</hi> &amp; alſo the wiſe man,<note place="margin">Ecleſiaſti 34.21.</note> 
                        <hi>he that offereth aſacrifice of the goode of the poore, is as he that ſacrificeth the ſonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fathers cies.</hi> What is this elſe, but as if a man ſhould ſteale a ſheepe, or a hog, and thinke to make ſatisfaction to his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in giuing the feete to the poore for Gods ſake. And therefore ſaith hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 34.18.</note> 
                        <hi>He that offereth an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of vnrighteous goods, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth a mocking ſacrifice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let vs herein lay before vs the example of famous <hi>Zacheus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 19.89</note> whoſe prayſe is in the Goſpell, and may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a miracle for the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larity of the fact. <hi>Behould</hi>
                        <pb n="146" facs="tcp:14604:80"/>(ſaith he) <hi>the halfe of my goods, I gine to the poore, and if I have taken from any man, by forged cauill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tion, I reſtors him foure fould.</hi> He loſt not his reward, for our <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> ſaide vnto him, <hi>This day is ſaluation come vnto this houſe, for aſmuch as he is alſo become the ſonne of Abraham.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the eight verſe, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny word, ſo many ſemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſo manydo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uments of mercy. He ſaith <hi>halfe of my goods,</hi> which may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ice, who either giue nothing to the poore, or ſo little, that it cannot relieue their want. When yet the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Hee thun ſoweth ſparingly,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> 
                        <hi>ſhal reape alſo ſparingly, and hee that ſoweth Liberally, ſhall reape alſo liberally.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:14604:80"/>
                     <p>Secondly, he ſayth (<hi>of my goods,</hi> a checke to our pride and delicacy, which will giue to the poore the refuſe only, and corrupt things, reſeruing all dainties (euen till we ſurfet) for our owne bellies.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, He addeth <hi>(my goods)</hi> to ſhew, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer giueth any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly gotten, doth but mocke in his ſacrifice, as I ſaide before.</p>
                     <p>In that hee ſaith <hi>(I giue)</hi> ſpeaking in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tenſe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demneth them which will do no good themſelues all their life time; but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all things, to the fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their executors, to be done after death.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly he promiſeth reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, of whatſoeuer hee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14604:81"/>had gotten vniuſtly, &amp; that in the largeſt manner, <hi>Foure fould,</hi> without which, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repentance, prayer, almeſdeedes, or any other worke of piety, is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God; For without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſtitution ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> repentance is neuer truely done, but counterfeited, but where it is truely done, the ſinne ſhal neuer bee pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, til the ſpoile be roſtored if it may poſſibly be done.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, he ſheweth to whom we ſhuld giue, when he addeth <hi>(vpon the waters)</hi> by which metaphor, he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not the elemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tary and materiall waters, but afflictions, anguiſhes, ſorrowes, aduerſities and miſeries, as <hi>Saue me O God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.1.88.7.</note> 
                        <hi>for the waters are entred euen
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14604:81"/>vpon my ſoule;</hi> by which hee vnderſtandeth his calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and aduerſities, which by their ſucceeding courſes like the waues of the ſea, ſeemed to ouerwhelme and drowne him. S. <hi>Ierome</hi> thus expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it. <hi>(Caſt thy bread vpon the waters)</hi> that is <hi>Iuxta aquas</hi> by the waters, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that as ſeede ſowne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fertile valeyes, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces well watred, yeeldes the more plentifull encreaſe; ſo ſaith he, hee that liberally diſtributeth his almes to ſuch as ſuffer miſery, and want, ſhall receiue a bleſſed reward, and an happie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt of the Lord; he ſoweth not a graine of ſeede, but bread it ſelfe, expecting the multiplication thereof with increaſe, and at the day of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14604:82"/>iudgement, he ſhall receiue much more then he gaue.</p>
                     <p>It is recorded that the Emperour <hi>Titus</hi> ſo loued li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, that remembring one euening with himſelfe, that hee had giuen nothing that day, ſaid; <hi>O my friends, we haue loſt this day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So let vs ſuppoſe that we haue loſt that day, and that houre, wherein ſome or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee not beneſitted by vs. Neither may I paſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſilence, the careful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard taken in this regard, by the Right Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, and bleſſed Martyr of Chriſt, Maſter <hi>Iohn Hooper,</hi> ſometimes Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and of <hi>Worceſter;</hi> who as Maſter <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> recordeth, neuer dined before hee had ſeene
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:14604:82"/>ſuch poore as vſually refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, (amounting many times to the number of eighty perſons and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) firſt catechized in the Principles of Religion, and afterwards ſufficiently comforted with bodily ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance. O bleſſed Biſhop that ſo bountifully fed both the ſoules and bodies of the poore flocke of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge: Oh that this example might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee forgotten amongſt vs. And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Iam. 2.16.</note> 
                        <hi>Albeit you ſay vnto the poore, depart in peace; war me your ſelues, fill your bellies,</hi> and the like: <hi>If notwithſtanding yee giue them not thoſe things that are needfull to the body, what helpeth it?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Surely of all that we poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſe,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:14604:83"/>we ſhall faue nothing, but what wee haue giuen to the poore, whereof God appointeth himſelfe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder, as done vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; <hi>Yea,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat 10.42</note> 
                        <hi>vnto a cup of cold water,</hi> whereby (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>Wee ſhall make our ſelues friends,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note> 
                        <hi>which ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs into euerlaſting Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou feareſt to looſe thy money by giuing it, and yet the beſtowing of it in almes is the meanes to keepe it; thou feareſt to looſe thy money by giuing it, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou not to looſe thy ſelfe by keeping it? For our goods auariciouſly reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, are not onely ſpoiled, but doe alſo ſpoile and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our ſpirits: Remember <hi>the wicked rich man, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14604:83"/>poore</hi> Lazarus, <hi>crauing a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>orſell of bread; doth now beg of him a drop of water to allay his heate.</hi> Laſtly, call to minde <hi>that God will iudge the wicked at the latter day, by their workes of mercy. Let vs therefore bee mercifull, as our Heauenly Father is mercifull.</hi> This ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the ſecond and third workes of mercy to the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Redimo.</head>
                     <p>THE fourth worke of mercy to the Body, conſiſteth in helping, relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, deliuering, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting thoſe that are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; touching which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Apoſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes ſaith;<note place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> 
                        <hi>Remember them that are in bonds, as thogh
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:14604:84"/>ye were bound with them.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay; Make their caſe your owne, deale with them as you would be dealt withall your ſelues, if the like miſery ſhould befall vnto you <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo ſaith,<note place="margin">Pro. 24.11.12.</note> 
                        <hi>Deliuer them that are drawne to death, and wile thou not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them that are led to bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaine? If thou ſay; Beheld, I know it not, hee that pondereth the hearts, doth not hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it? and hee that keepeth thy ſoule, knowes hee it not? will hee not alſo recompence euery man according to his workes?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſhewes, that if we ſee thoſe that be vnrightcouſly drawne to death, or oppioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, wee muſt not ſtand by, and ſay; <hi>Alaſſo, who euer ſam ſuch a World as this is? who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaw ſuch wrongfull appreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14604:84"/>vſed, as in theſe times?</hi> But wee muſt put to our helping hand, and labour to our power to reſcue them, and to deliuer them: For, ſaith he, <hi>Wilt not thou preſerue them?</hi> As if he had ſaid; Art thou ſo merciſeſſe, that thou wilt not helpe the oppreſſed? But then he meets with our excuſes, which we are ready to make in ſuch caſes: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe, I knew not that hee had ſuch neede of my helpe, or if I ſhould meddle, I ſhould bring an old houſe vpon mine owne head, and trouble my ſelfe, when I needed not:</hi> yet he cuts off all, when he ſaith; <hi>Doth not God ſee thee, and know thy heart?</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay; <hi>Well theſe excuſes may dazell mine eyes, and make a faire ſhew with them, that can ſee nothing but
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14604:85"/>ſhewes; but God lookes not ſo much to the tongue, and what one can ſay for himſelfe; he pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the heart, and that not lightly; he knowes and conſiders euery particular thing and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuneſtance: and therefore it is no ſhifting, nor doubling, when he comes to take triall of vs.</hi> For he knowes that all thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes come from ſelfe-loue, and the loue of lucre, and commodity; that one might ſpare coſt, and liue at caſe, and rather ſee another op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with wrong, then hazard himſelfe any way to helpe him.</p>
                     <p>Laſt of all hee ſaith; <hi>You that be ſo loath to ſuffer a little trouble, and to bee at a little charges to helpe another man in miſery; know you not that God recompenceth men accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14604:85"/>to their workes?</hi> That hee cauſeth them to reape like for like; may not you come to the like miſery your ſelf? and then becauſe you had no heart, nor will to helpe another, you ſhall ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fit as quietly by you, and not venture to miniſter any ſuccour vnto you.</p>
                     <p>Now men are come to ſuch ſelfe-loue, and ſenſleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of other mens wrongs, as if they were things done in a farre Countrey, and in another age, as if it nothing appertained to them, they haue nothing to doe with them. The better fort onely will haue a little idle pitty, and mercy in the mouth; ſaying: <hi>Alaſſe, I am ſorry, and it is a pitty, that honeſt men ſhould be thus wronged, iniured,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14604:86"/>and diſgraced;</hi> yet they will neuer put to an hand to helpe, they will not ſtirre a finger, to doe any good to their reliefe: neither will they take any paines, or be at any charges, to eaſe and deliuer the oppreſſed: for moſt men beare this minde, that they could take more paines, and ſpend more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to compaſſe their owne pleaſures, to ſatiſſie their luſts, and carnall appetites; yea, to pul one of their own beaſts out of the ditch, then to deliuer a poore wronged Chriſtian out of the pawes of the perſecutor. But <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than was not of this minde,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20.38.</note> 
                        <hi>hee ventured his owne life to ſaue Dauids, and deliuered him out of the hand of Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l his Father, though it ſeemed Dauid onely
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14604:86"/>ſtood betweene him and the Crowne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obadiah likewiſe being A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs Steward,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Kin. 18.4</note> 
                        <hi>when his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter raiſed an hot perſecution, and would haue ſlaine all the Prophets of God; and hee in likelihood ſhould haue eſcaped: but hardly, if his Maſter had perceiued that hee had borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fauour and affection towards them; and the famine was ſo great, that ſcarce bread and water could bee got for money.</hi> So that it was not onely dangerous, but exceeding chargeable to feede an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Prophets now, whom the King ſought with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to bring to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: yet (notwithſtanding all theſe impediments) <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah</hi> ſtood faithfully for God and his Prophets, <hi>and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14604:87"/>kept them with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſufficiently, both in the heate of perſecution, and in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of famine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But on the contrary, moſt helliſh and curſed of all are thoſe, that be ſo farre from helping and ſuccouring Gods afflicted Saints, as that they reioyce at their troubles, recounting it one to another as very ioyfull tidings, and matter of meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they heare that ſuch a man is in priſon, ſuch a Miniſter ſuſpended, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or the like; yea, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture they will not ſticke to put an hand to it, and to their power, to helpe it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Theſe be cruel wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches indeede, inſpired with the malice of the Diuell, &amp; (vnleſſe they repent) ſhall
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14604:87"/>bee moſt miſerable hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being plagued with the vengeance of God, as a iuſt recompence for their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: whereas in this caſe, they ought rather ſo to ſhew mercy vnto others, as they would expect the mercy of God towards themſelues. <hi>Let vs therefore bee mercifull, as our Heauenly Father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus much touching the fourth worke of mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Tego.</head>
                     <p>THE fift worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the body, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in ſhewing mercy to the poore and needy, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our ability, &amp; their neceſſity: This duty our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt commandeth,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14604:88"/>ſaying;<note place="margin">Luk. 12.33</note> 
                        <hi>Sell that you haue, and make you bag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> that waxe not olde.</hi> VVhere Chriſt exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs to bee mercifull, meetes with a common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection: Indeede I would willingly beſtow ſomthing vpon the poore members of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> but laſſe, I haue nothing. Haue you nothing to ſel; neuer a ſtrike of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orn, neuer a parcell of Land, no Merchandize, no houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> old ſtuffe, that you could ſpare for <hi>Chriſt?</hi> If you haue, ſell it, and giue to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to his Members; imitating therein a wicked man, who to compaſſe his pleaſures, and to ſatiſſie his owne car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appetite, will come by money, what ſhift ſoeuer he make: Doe you as much for Chriſt and his Members, as
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14604:88"/>a wicked man will doe for the fulfilling of his vaine deſires. <hi>Oh, but if I ſhould ſell, and giue, ſo I might be begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Nay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> wils no man to beggar himſelfe: <hi>But make you bags.</hi> This is ſuch a treaſure, as no other is like it; for no other will multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie and increaſe, lying by vs, but is of that nature, that either of it ſelfe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> will cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, the canker and ruſt wil ſet vpon it, and bring it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ught; or elſe a thiefe may meete with it, ſo that one is in continuall danger to bee poore. But this is ſuch a kind of treaſure, as in it ſelfe is eternal, and growing, and is ſo ſurely kept, that no man can depriue vs of it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by force or craft. And then another benefit there
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14604:89"/>is;<note place="margin">Luk. 12.34</note> 
                        <hi>Where your treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo.</hi> This is of ſo good effect, that if one lay vp treaſure in Heauen, his heart will follow it.</p>
                     <p>What is the reaſon then that many men can come ſo hardly to ſpeake of Heauen, and heauenly things? that one may as eaſily make a great milſtone aſcend vp to the Skie, as draw their thoughts to heauen-ward; the reaſon is plaine, their treaſure is not there. This knew <hi>Salomon,</hi> when hee ſaid;<note place="margin">Pro. 11.17</note> 
                        <hi>He that is mercifull to the poore, rewardeth his owne ſoule.</hi> As if he had ſaid; euery man will yeeld it is a good thing to bee beneficiall to himſelfe, and to doe good to his owne ſoule: but it is moſt certaine, that nothing
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14604:89"/>in the VVorld, no purchaſe, no bargaine, ſhall bring ſo much profit to the ſoule, as a mercifull heart, and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall hand to the poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Acts 9.39.</note> This cauſed <hi>Dorcas to bee ſo full of good workes and almes, whoſe continuall cuſtome was to buy cloth, cut it forth, and prepare garments for the naked.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Maſter <hi>Fox</hi> recordeth, in the ſtory of the Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lady, the Lady <hi>Anne Bullen,</hi> Mother to the late Queene of famous memory, Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> that ſhee vſually ſent her meſſengers into the Townes next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning to her abode, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand both the number, and ſtate of their poore; and where greateſt want was, ſhee contributed her almes
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:14604:90"/>to the reliefe of their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; yea, and that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, ſo great was her compaſſion towards the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Gods people. Let vs then by theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Remember them that are in bonds,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> 
                        <hi>as though wee alſo were bound with them; and them that are afflicted, as if we alſo were afflicted.</hi> Neither let the rich man thinke (whom wealth and nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty maketh haughty and proud) that therefore hee was formed of gold, ſiluer, or ſome purer ſubſtance, then the beggar, who hath nothing to ſtand vpon, but beggery, patchery, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury: for of the ſame maſſe, of the ſame vile, and abiect peece of earth, both rich &amp; poore were taken. Let them
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:14604:90"/>againe remember, that they are mortall, corruptible, fraile, and ſubiect to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chances and changes as any other, though neuer ſo poore and contemptible in the world. <hi>Iob</hi> hauing found this by experience, <hi>Would not ſee any periſh for want of cloathing,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iob 31.19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>nor any poore without conering; yea many bleſſed him, that were warmed with the fleece of his ſheepe.</hi> And hee found the truth of that bleſſing pronounced by the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſaying; <hi>Bleſſed is the man that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the poore and needy,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1</note> 
                        <hi>the Lord ſhall deliuer him in the time of trouble.</hi> VVhy then deſpiſeſt thou thine owne fleſh? why art thou an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to thy ſelfe? This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ſhould breede in
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14604:91"/>vs ſuch a fellow-feeling of the good, or euill; ioy, or ſorrow; weale, or woe of the members of the ſame body; that wee ſhould <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with them that reioyce,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 12.16</note> 
                        <hi>and weep with them that weepe.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.25.</note> 
                        <hi>That the members ſhould haue the ſame care one of another:</hi> Otherwiſe, if wee haue loſt this feeling, and affection of members, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth plainely, that wee be no true members of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body, that we are not ingrafted into the body of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> aſſureth vs;<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.17</note> 
                        <hi>That whoſoeuer hath this Worlds goods, and ſeeth his brother hath neede, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him, that the loue of God cannot dwel in him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If then the loue of God
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:14604:91"/>be in thy heart, it is knowne by the loue that thou ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to thy neighbour: and if thou loueſt thy neighbour, thou wilt not ſhew thy ſelfe hard-hearted, and ſtraight laced vnto him in his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Euen as the heart that is placed in the middeſt of the body, inclineth moſt to the left ſide, though indeed it inſpireth life to the whole body: ſo though a Chriſtian ought to manifeſt his loue to euery man, and our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is to bee diffuſed vnto all men; yet ſhould hee bee moſt prone to the afflicted part, and to beſtow his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable beneuolence, where there is moſt neede of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
                     <p>Charity and loue to our neighbour in humane ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:14604:92"/>is like the blood in the naturall body, which amine ſtreth and conſerueth life: for as the blood in euery ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the body run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the indigent parts, to ſuccour where is moſt need; ſo is true charity ouer readie to miniſter ſuccour, and to conuert it ſelfe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where is moſt need and neceſſity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lucullus</hi> hauing ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly entertained (for ſome time) certain Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cians; and when they ſaid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vnto him, they maruelled that for their ſakes hee would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſuch liberall expence, and magnificent coſt; be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: <hi>Much my friends was for your ſakes, but the greateſt part was for Lucullus</hi> ſake: So the good Chriſtian who
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:14604:92"/>ſheweth himſelfe mercifull to the poore &amp; needy, doth ſurely much for their ſakes, becauſe hee loueth them as his neighbours and fellow members: but much alſo for his owne ſake, becauſe hee is delighted in doing good, and ioyfully doth the worke of mercy.</p>
                     <p>The Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares our deeds of charity to ſeede ſowne;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
                        <hi>They that ſow plentifully, ſhall reape alſo plentifully.</hi> Now wee know that after ſowing, in time comes the Harueſt; and when the harueſt commeth, there is many for one: the Husbandmans labour is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced; keep your ſeed by you, it will corrupt, caſt it forth, it ſhall bring in creaſe.</p>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:14604:93"/>
                     <p>VVhat more praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in a Chriſtian, then where God hath bleſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie gathered, and fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſaued; thereby charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble almeſdeeds, and workes of mercy, to pittie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed eſtates of others, eſpecially conſidering, that if we ſow but a cup of cold water in conſcience, and in loue, it is ſowne vpon <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 25.35</note> he is the ground: <hi>For I was hungry, and ye gaue mee meate; I thirſted, and ye gaue mee drinke; I was a ſtranger, and ye lodged me, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore vnleſſe yee thinke that Chriſt will bee a barren ground, it is moſt certaine, that he which ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſeede here, ſhall reape a large increaſe: that which is caſt abroade in mercy, ſhall
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14604:93"/>returne againe in goodnes; the more good a man doth, the more good hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue: for God will reſtore it.</p>
                     <p>But oh what vaine of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, or ſtile of perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, may now ſerue in this congealed age of charity, to mollifie the ſteely hearts, and thaw the frozen affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of worldlings, and make them relent at the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt? Let vs neuer forget that the ſentence which the ſupreame Iudge <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhall pronounce at the dreadful day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall be grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the workes of mercy, how wee haue diſcharged our ſtewardſhip in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and reliefe, or in the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:14604:94"/>neglect and contempt of his poore members, which hee reputeth as done vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>And contrariwiſe, he ſhall ſend the mercileſſe, and ſuch as haue heene negligent in the workes of charitie, into eternall fire. Of earefull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, to be tormented with the Diuell and his Angels: Oh that this ſentence were continually ſounding in our eares.</p>
                     <p>But you are to note, that theſe workes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, are not here ſet downe as the cauſes, whereby men merit ſaluation; but becauſe theſe workes of charity, are the infallible fruits of our faith, to ſhew the ſame to be liuely, <hi>and working through loue;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> and ſo conſequently,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14604:94"/>the markes and ſignes of our election, and that way wherein God would haue vs to walke towards the poſſeſſion of his heauenly Kingdome.</p>
                     <p>Many men, pretend many excuſes, that they may not giue, ſome for feare of dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their goods, that if they extend liberally to the poore, they themſelues ſhall want; others, cut of their bounty to the poore vnder pretence of prouiding for their children, that they may leaue them the richer but what is this elſe, but to diſtruſt God, then not to be lieue his word, then not to truſt him vpon his promiſe? Hath not truth it ſelfe ſaid, which cannot lie?<note place="margin">Pro. 28.27.</note> 
                        <hi>Hee that giuth to the poore, ſhall not
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14604:95"/>want.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luke 6.38</note> Likewiſe doth not our Saniour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay, <hi>Giue, and it ſhall bee giuen you, a good meaſure, preſſed downe, ſhaken together, and running ouer, ſhall men giue into your boſome.</hi> And doth not God aſſure thee, that this <hi>honouring of God with thy ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 3.9.</note> ſhal be ſo far from diminiſhing thy wealth. <hi>That it ſhall fill thy barnes with aboundance.</hi> And doth not the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.10</note> 
                        <hi>That God will mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply your ſeede; and increaſe the fruite of your benenolence.</hi> If thou wouldeſt prouide for thy children, what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe canſt thou take, then that which S. <hi>Ciprian</hi> giueth. If thou haſt many children, be the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by diſtributing to the poore, to leaue them Gods
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14604:95"/>bleſſing; commit to his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, the goods thou wouldeſt lay vppe for thy children, make God their tutor, and protectour, and ſo ſhalt thou be ſure to haue them ſafe kept. Otherwiſe thy niggardlineſſe, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>the poore, to make them rich, what is it elſe, but a ſubuerſion of thy ſelfe thy houſe, and thy children?</p>
                     <p>We are all not Lords, but Gods ſtewrds; of the goods commited to our charge, and the poore be but Gods receiuers, which come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Gods bleſſings at our hands, to deny then to pay vnto thee poore, (which beare Gods <hi>Image</hi>) that which we owe vnto God, what is this, but an heinous theft, and an intollerable
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:14604:96"/>ſacriledge? <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) giue vnto mee of that which I haue giuen thee, I aske but mine owne, giue, and reſtore, thou haſt found me liberall, make me thy debtor, thou giueſt vnto me temporall things, I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto thee eternall. Sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, there is nothing more diſhonoureth God, then diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>obedience and diſtruſt in his prouidence, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for it deroguteth from his goodnes, as if he would ſuffer vs to want, if we obey his will. Euen as mothers, which haue many ſmall children, haue ouer bread by them, that they may giue vnto their children, when they craue; ſo our God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth with all treaſures of goodneſſe, and is ready
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:14604:96"/>to impart vnto thoſe that ſerue him, and craue at his hands. As did the Leaper,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.</note> 
                        <hi>Maſter if thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane.</hi> Then would the Lord preſently anſwer, <hi>I will, be thou cleane:</hi> thou ſhalt haue ſufficient, thou haſt obeyed my will, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reliefe vnto the poore I will not faile thee,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note> nor for ſake thee. <hi>Make you friends</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>of the unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Mammon, that when you ſhall want they may receiue you into euerlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Damaſoene</hi> telleth a tale of the rich mans three friends, his goods, his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, and his workes of charity.</p>
                     <p>His goods when he dieth, can afford him but a ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:14604:97"/>ſheete, &amp; a few mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſo forſake him; his kinsfolke follow him to the graue, and there leaue him; but his almeſdeedes, and vertues neuer forſake him. This, this, I ſay is the friend wee ſhould moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and as for the droſſe of the world, and all other friends we muſt leaue them, and they will forſake vs. And ſurely there is nothing more effectuall, to the good of a family, then when the Maſter of it opens his hands aboundantly, with all plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of good workes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. I will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this fift-branch, with this ſaying.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Who helpes the poore, and pittieth the oppreſſed,</l>
                        <pb n="181" facs="tcp:14604:97"/>
                        <l>He liues to God, and doubtleſſe dieth bleſſed.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let vs therefore be merciful as our heauenly father, is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi> And thus much tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the fift worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Colligo.</head>
                     <p>THe ſixt worke of mercy to the body, conſiſteth in lodging the harbourleſſe and in the entertaining of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers. And this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth vnto vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Receiue yee one another,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 15.7</note> 
                        <hi>as Chriſt alſo receiued vs to the glory of the father.</hi> But ſo great was the loue of Chriſt that he ſticked not to offer vp his body, and bloud as a liuely ſacrifice to God the father for our attonement
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:14604:98"/>and reconciliation. How great then ſhould ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſtian loue be one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another to further the good one of another &amp; to relieue the wants &amp; neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties one of another. The Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth to vs with a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.2.</note> ſaying; <hi>Be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull to entertaine ſtrangers, for thereby ſome haue entertai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned Angels into their houſe vnawares.</hi> Wherein he ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth an obiection made by many, ſaying, <hi>I could be willing to entertaine any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, but I did not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that any ſtranger paſt by my dore at any time vnregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> Did you not? And why I pray you, would you be ſo forgetfull? can you tell to whom you denied enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14604:98"/>and vpon what occaſion they trauailed this way.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.1.2.</note> 
                        <hi>For had not Let enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the two Angels, when hee ſaw them, he might (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduonture) haue had his deſtruction amongſt them of Sedom &amp; Gomorrah.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Kings 17 10.22.</note> 
                        <hi>Had not the widdow of Sarcphath enter tained Elias, neither could ſhe haue continued her meale in her barrel, nor her oyle in her cruſe, neither had her ſonne dying bin reſtored to life.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioſua 2.1.</note> 
                        <hi>And Rahab had not ſaued her ſelfe &amp; her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold neither could ſhe haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this priuiledge, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Chriſt Ieſus according to the fleſh, ſhould haue come of her ſtocke &amp; poſterity, if ſhe had not entertained, and defended with the hazard of her owne life thoſe ſpies, which Ioſua ſent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is recorded that the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans</hi>
                        <pb n="184" facs="tcp:14604:99"/>had a law; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned that man to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which ſuffered a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to paſſe vnlodged, after the ſunne was downe. And ſurely, were the like law in <hi>England,</hi> practiſed vpon our Inhoulders, and victualling houſes, our poore trauailers ſhould be better reſpected.</p>
                     <p>For albeit the law tolerate thoſe houſes, rather for the reliefe of ſtrangers, then for the maintenance of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and other ſhifting mates. Let a trauailer neuer theleſſe, be his occaſion neuer ſo vrgent) reſort to any of them, who either is not able, or willing, ſo to lauiſh his expences, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their greedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, (albeit otherwiſe they will content them to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:14604:99"/>the vttermoſt farthing) yet will they turne him away, bid him be gon, and tel him their Roomes are prouided for others. And truely theſe abuſes I haue had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of, and therefore may well ſing with <hi>Dido.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Non Ignara mali, miſeris ſuccurrere diſco.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The knowledge of this euill, mooueth me to pittie thoſe that are thus afflicted.</p>
                     <p>Your Sergeants and Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leues in the ſecond place are to be found fault withall, and that for two cauſes; firſt for their iugling &amp; double dealing with men. If they be well contented, they can play ſee me, and ſee me not; yea albeit they goe daily by the party, and the credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor be at great coſt and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:14604:100"/>charges with them, for at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taching of their debtors. But if the debtor giue not to them ſuch reward as they expect, then let him looke to himſelfe, he ſhall be cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, dragd, and haled to priſon, he ſhal be pincht &amp; flieced to the bare bones, yea they will hardly leaue, till they haue pluckt from him all that hoe is able to make I might t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, for their bad and vnconſcionable dealing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards orphans, and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children: many being ſo barely flieced by thoſe, into whoſe tuition &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection they haue beene committed, that they can ſcarce recouer from them ten for a hundred, towards their reliefe and ſuſtenance.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14604:100"/>So hard harted are many in theſe our dayes, and of ſo woluiſh a nature, that in ſtead of education, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, they will giue them their baine and deſtruction, iniuriouſly wreſting from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almoſt al, that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their bands. But let them beware, &amp; take heede leaſt the Lord, who heareth the cry of the poore, and appreſſed, reward them not accordingly.</p>
                     <p>I could alſo blame hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Chirurgions and Phiſitians in Hoſpitals, who hauing often times poore patients vnder their cure, continue them in torture, and paine, ſuffering them grieuouſly to languiſh in their maladies, becauſe they cannot extort from them
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14604:101"/>ſuch ſummes of money, as they would. But God, who alſo deliuereth all his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> out of their hands, will one day call theſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and pay them their hire in hell, vnleſſe by repentance they preuent Gods iudgement ſpeedily.</p>
                     <p>What ſhould I ſay to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and ouer-ſeers to the guifts of the dead, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times conuert and turne thoſe things to their owne gaine, and proſit, which the deceaſed, by will bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, towards the reliefe of the poore, the nake, the halt &amp; the blind? I ſay, if there be any ſuch, let them be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, and wary yea let their repentance be quick, and ſpeedy, leaſt God in his iudgement ouertake them.</p>
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:14604:101"/>
                     <p>I could alſo touch water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the behauiour of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the moſt part is ſo rude, irreuerent, and curriſh that they will ſcarce ſpare, or for beare any ſtate, age, perſon, or ſex.</p>
                     <p>But I will conclude with the laylour, whoſe oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and extorting cruelty towards the poore priſoner is vnſupportable. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer falleth into his hands though he enter with a full purſe, yet ſhall he be ſure to haue it empty before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture; being during, his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in priſon, entertaiend with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, cold iron, &amp; fees enough, for his reliefe, and comfort. Theſe mercileſſe miſers, ſhew to none any fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſeration, then they themſelues may haue a large
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:14604:102"/>conſideration. But let them hearken to Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euerlaſting fire,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41</note> 
                        <hi>prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.</hi> For if euery man be bound to giue to the reliefe of the needy, what ſhall we thinke of thoſe men, who not only neuer practiſe this leſſon of giuing, but alſo by alſubtile meanes, cunning ſhifts, fraudulent dealing, poll, &amp; pill, oppreſſe, wring, couſen and deceiue the poore, and catch that little they haue, from them? who feed them ſelues with others wants, cloath themſelue, by others nakedues, pamper vp them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues by others penurie.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.4</note> 
                        <hi>Surely this crieth into the eares of the Lord of hoaſts, who being a righteous Iudge,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14604:102"/>and the God to whom ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance onely belongeth, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them accordingly. Si ſterilitas in Ignom mittitur, ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ita quid meretur?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note> If barren neſſeſhould be caſt into the fire, what doth catching &amp; rapine deſerue?<note place="margin">Iames 2.3</note> If the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>There ſhall be iudgement without mercy, to him that ſheweth no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> what iudgement (thinke you) belongeth to him, which doth alſo ſhew cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to the poore? <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat qui aliena tulit, ſi ſemper ardebit, qui ſua non dedit</hi> what ſhall he receiue that taketh away other mens goods, if hee ſhall euer burne in hell fire,<note place="margin">Rabunus</note> that hath not giuen of his owne? I was an hungred ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thou gaueſt me no meate, nay the little
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14604:103"/>meate I had, thou tookeſt from me, I was naked, and thou gaueſt me no cloathes, nay the poore cloathes I had, thou tookeſt from me Is there an <hi>Item aledicti,</hi> for them which doe not feede the hungry, and ſhall they goe free, which take away the bread of the hungry. Is the puniſhment ſo great for them that lodge not the ſtrangers, and is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them, that wrong the fatherleſſe, and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? If thoſe who cloathed not the naked, finde it ſo hard a doome, what may they feare, that take away the cloathing of the naked. S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> (in his thirtie &amp; fourth <hi>Homily to the people of Antioch</hi>) ſayth, that whatſoeuer is a boue
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:14604:103"/>our neceſſary maintenance, is not ours, but the goods of the poore, and to retaine this from them, cryeth into the eares of the Lord for ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance. And ſurely, there will come a day, when men would wiſh they had beene more mercifull. <hi>For with what meaſure you meate,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 6.38.</note> 
                        <hi>with the ſame ſhall men meate to you againe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Innumerable are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, of like meaſure of Gods iuſtice towards the vnmerciful, worthy the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, to teach vs the neceſſity of mercy towards our neighbours, if wee would auoid the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Gods reuenging hand for our cruelty ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to others.</p>
                     <p>It is recorded by <hi>Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi>
                        <pb n="204" facs="tcp:14604:104"/>in his Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory,<note place="margin">Lib 1. Cap. 29.</note> that the dancing daughter or <hi>Herodias,</hi> who required of wicked <hi>Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> the head of inndent Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and had it, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards going on ſoote ouer a hard frozen riuer, the ice breaking, ſhe ſunke downe euen vnto the necke, which, (through the violence of a great piece of ice comming downe the riuer) was cut off from thereſt other body, and ſo ſhe taſted of the like death, ſhe procured to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>King Dauid</hi> at his death,<note place="margin">1 King 2.5</note> gaue charge to <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, <hi>Thou knoweſt what Ioab did; he ſtird the bloud of battaile in the time of peace, &amp; put the bloud of warre vpon his girdle, that was aboute
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:14604:104"/>his loines, and in his ſhooes; that were on his feete: let not his gray head go down to the graue in peace.</hi> Wherefore he was afterward ſlaine, taking hould on the hornes of the altar, and ſo the Lord did bring his bloud vpon his owne head.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aelianus</hi> reporteth of one <hi>Cratenas</hi> who vilanouſly ſlew <hi>Archilaus tirant</hi> of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia</hi> (of whom hee was entirely beloued) that hee might make a compendious way vnto the kingdome, but hee taſted of the ſame ſauce. For he had ſcarce en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed the kingdome three dayes, before hee was alſo ſlaine, fulfilling the verſe of <hi>Dramatus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="206" facs="tcp:14604:105"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Qui ſtruit Inſidias alijs, ſihi damna dat ipſi.</hi> (wrought. Hee that hath ſnares for others Himſelf the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n is likwiſe caught.</p>
                     <p>This ſhall ſuffice to ſhew how God in his deepe and vnſearcheable prouidence puniſheth (yea in this life) cruell and vnmercifull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with the ſame meaſure that they meate vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Meſſem</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>'Bernard</hi>) <hi>habebis, ſemente dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam;</hi> thy harueſt ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy ſowing: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſericordiam ſeminaſti, habe quodamaſti;</hi> haſt thou ſowed vnmercifulnes? receiue what thou loueſt, <hi>Fugiſti miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam? te fugit miſericordia:</hi> Didſt thou fly mercy? mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will fly from thee. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatus es pauperem? deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur te qui propter nos, factus
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:14604:105"/>eſt pauper:</hi> Doeſt thou hate the poore? He will alſo hate thee, who for our ſakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came poore. Where is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the large liberallitie of old benefactours, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore members of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> Is not all (with many) ſcant ſufficient to maintaine our exceſſes? The pride of the world in attire, and the maintenance thereof, in lauiſhing the the needleſſe ſuperfluity of diet, hath eaten vp hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and mercy toward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hungry ſoules, &amp; it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that wee haue little to leaue at our departure, for the good of others. Neuer more at table, neuer leſſe at door; neuer more ſumtuous in cloathing our ſelues, ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er leſſe reſpect of others:
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:14604:106"/>Nature is content with few things, all will not ſerue out exceſſe. Let vs therefore be ſo ſparing in ſuperfluous ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pences, that we may be the more liberall towards mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and charitable vſes; yea, let vs be kinde &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful on towards another as wee hope for mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father. <hi>Let vs therefore be merciful as &amp;c.</hi> Thus much touching the ſixt worke of mercy to the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Condo.</head>
                     <p>THE laſt worke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards the body, conſiſteth in burying the dead; touching which duty the Wiſe man ſaith: <hi>My ſon, poure forth thy teares ouer the dead,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 38.16.</note> 
                        <hi>then couer his body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his appointment, and
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:14604:106"/>neglect not his buriall.</hi> The ſame commandement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>Tobit</hi> to his Sonne;<note place="margin">Tobit 14.10.</note> 
                        <hi>My Sonne when I die, burie me ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</hi> VVhence we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſunerall rites, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent interring of corpes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equies, and ſeemely mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, (which Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> calleth, <hi>Officium poſtremi mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris,</hi> our laſt duties of loue) are not vnfitting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe of thoſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt whom all things ſhould be done in order. The Iſraelites in bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying ſo honourably their Parents and Gouernours, did ſhew themſelues to be people of good and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſitions. <hi>Abraham the Father of the faithfull,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 23.4.</note> 
                        <hi>bought a poſſeſſion of buriall of the Hittites, who by the ſight and light of nature, had their
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:14604:107"/>Sepulchers: And therefore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered Abraham; Thou art a Prince of God amongſt vs, in the chiefeſt of our Sepulchers bury thy dead, none of vs ſhall forbid thee his Sepulcher; but thou maieſt burie thy dead therein.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 25.</note> 
                        <hi>So when Abraham yeelded the ſpirit, and died in a good age, and was gathered to his people; his Sonnes Iſaac and Iſmael buried him in the care of Machepelah, in the field of Hephron, where Abraham was buried with Sarah his wife.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The like wee ſee done to <hi>Iſaac, when hee gaue vp the ghoſt being old and ful of daies; his two Sonnes, Eſau and Iacob buried him.</hi> Now as <hi>Iacob</hi> did to his Father, ſo his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe to him, according as he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded them: <hi>For they carried him into the
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:14604:107"/>Land of Canaan, and buried him in the caue of the field of Machpelah, which Abraham had bought.</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Moſes:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 34.56.</note> 
                        <hi>for albeit the people buried him not, neither knew of his Sepulcher, leſt they ſhould abuſe it to Idolatry: yet rather then hee ſhould want bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, he was buried of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The men of Iabeſh Gilead,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.5, 6.</note> 
                        <hi>are praiſed of God, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Dauid, becauſe they bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried King Saul and his Sonne, and aduentured their liues to doe vnto him their laſt duty.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſame might be ſaide of the reſt of the Patriarkes, Prophets, Iudges, Kings, Gouernours, and Prieſts: <hi>Yea, the new Sepulcher,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 23.53</note> 
                        <hi>the cleane linnen cloathes the ſweet ointments, and the aſſembly of men of reputation, ſhewed how
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:14604:108"/>our Sauiour was reſpectiuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and entembed with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>nity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe examples teach, that it is a Chriſtian and commendable duty of the liuing, to bee performed to the dead; of Children to be performed to their Parents, of the people of God one towards another, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the body of the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the graue, to put duſt to duſt, and ſo to couer earth with earth.</p>
                     <p>And certainely thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which haue beene the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhall bee at the day of doome changed into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of glory; ſhould haue that decencie performed, as is agreeable both to comely practiſe, &amp; Chriſtian ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe:
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:14604:108"/>wherefore, as they are very highly to bee exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whoſe honourable care to the dead is ſuch, as to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them Tombes, and to repaire and beautifie their decayed Monuments: ſo on the other ſide, they are greatly to bee reproued, and found fault withal, that careleſly attend to the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of their brethren depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                     <p>But what ſhall I ſay to ſuch as deface the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the dead? Surely ſuch deſerue to haue their names to be blotted out of good mens remembrance, for ſuch their cruell, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and barbarous dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: whereas they ought rather to beautifie the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memories, and repaire
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:14604:109"/>the decaied tombes of their Anceſtors, and Forefathers.</p>
                     <p>Let vs I ſay, in this laſt point of loue alſo, ſo ſhew mercy vnto others, as wee would likewiſe expect in the ſame caſe to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med towards our ſelues, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially it being a matter of ſo great weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>For firſt amongſt all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Man is moſt loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and vgly, when his life is departed: as in his birth &amp; bringing forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the VVorld, of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hee is moſt fraile and feeble, without ſtrength to ſtand, without helpe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe; ſo being dead, he is become noyſom, gaſtly and deformed: hee that a little before gloried
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:14604:109"/>of his beauty, comelineſſe, feature, and proportion, is now become the mirrour &amp; ſpectacle of a deformed, miſhapen, and noyſom car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe: ſuch a confuſion and wracke hath ſinne wrought and brought into our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. This is noted in <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.39</note> 
                        <hi>who hauing lien buried but foure dayes, his body ſtunke.</hi> Secondly, buriall is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a bleſſing from God, and the want of it threatned for a plague and iudgement. God offereth it as a mercy to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 15.15</note> 
                        <hi>that he ſhould be buried in a ripe age: and to Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, that he ſhould be put in his graue in peace,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 King. 22.19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>and his eyes ſhould not behold the euill that ſhould bee brought vpon that place.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Contrariwiſe, the want
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:14604:110"/>hereof is threatned as a curſe to <hi>Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and <hi>Ahab, Kings of Iſrael, that they and their poſterity ſhould be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with dogs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And becauſe <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> fell from God, it was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde vnto him by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; <hi>That hee ſhould not bee buried honourably, but he ſhould be buried as an Aſſe is buried, euen drawne, and caſt forth without the gates of Ieruſalem.</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                        </label> But ſome will obiect, that the faithfull often times want buriall; ſome conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to aſhes, ſome drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the waters, ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of wild beaſts, ſome hanged on gibbets, of whom the VVorld was not worthy, as the Prophet complayneth; <note place="margin">Pſal. 79.2, 3.</note> 
                        <hi>The dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of thy Seruants haue they
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:14604:110"/>giuen to be meate to the Fowles of the Heauen, and the fleſh of thy Saints vnto the heaſts of the Earth; their blood haue they ſhed like waters round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Ieruſalem, and there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> to bury them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">Reſol.</note> all temporall chaſtiſements are common to the godly, and vngodly, as famin, plague, peſtilence, ſword, nakedneſſe, and ſuch like puniſhments, which God ſhooteth as his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes againſt the ſonnes of men. The fauour of God bringing ſaluation, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in theſe outward things: for as it cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit a wicked and wretched man to bee ſolemnly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and coſtly buried, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the fauour of God, <hi>(As is noted in the
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:14604:111"/>Parable of the rich glutton)</hi> ſo it ſhall not hurt a righteous man,<note place="margin">Luk. 10 22, 23.</note> to want a ſumptuous ſolemnizing of his fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
                     <p>Yet let vs make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the body of man and beaſt: for as man differeth from the beaſt in his life;<note place="margin">Gen. 2.7.</note> 
                        <hi>Made after the image of God,</hi> faſhioned to looke vpward, <hi>created with a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule,</hi> and ſundry other prerogatiues; ſo hee ſhould in his death and buriall. The bodies of beaſts are drawne forth being dead, to lie in the open aire, to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one of another, and it skilleth not: but it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely, and vnlawfull, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt order and honeſty, that the dead bodies of men ſhould be caſt out vnburied
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:14604:111"/>into ditches, and dunghils, or ſuch foule and filthy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And therefore <hi>Iehuſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Iezabel,</hi> caſt downe out of her window, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her blood ſprinckled vpon the wall, ſaid; <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſit now yonder curſed woman,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 King. 9.34.</note> 
                        <hi>and bury her.</hi> Seeing then that the dead carkaſſe of man is ſo vnſauoury and loathſom by reaſon of ſinne, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buriall is a bleſſing where it is beſtowed, and a curſe where it is denied; we conclude, that it is a courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and commendable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, teſtifying our loue and reuerence to the dead, ſo ſoone as life is departed, and death hath arreſted them, to commit the body to the graue.</p>
                     <p>And thus haue I (albeit
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:14604:112"/>in a weake meaſure) parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſet downe what I could, touching each duty of mercy, both to ſoule and body, deſiring, and humbly beſeeching all thoſe, into whoſe hands this Treatiſe ſhall happen, ſo to ſhew mercy vnto others, as they would haue mercy as the hands, of God towardes themſelues. <hi>Les vs therefore hee mercifull as our Heauenly Father is mercifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus much touching the precept.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Preſident.</head>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <hi>In theſe words.</hi> As your father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is merciful.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt, whereas <hi>Chriſt</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs to call God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee are emboldned to
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:14604:112"/>make our ſuits vnto him, leaſt we might ſay as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham what be we,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 18.27.</note> 
                        <hi>which are but duſt and aſhes, to talke vnto God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, when wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide him as a father, in the very beginning of our prayer, wee acknowledge his bounty and grace. For firſt this name of father, is a name to moue vs to come vnto him.</p>
                     <p>The wandring ſonne ſaid <hi>Ibo adpatrem.</hi> I will goe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my father.<note place="margin">Luk. 15.18</note> Secondly it is a name of priuiledge.<note place="margin">Rom 8.18.</note> 
                        <hi>Hee hath giuen vs</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>his ſpirit, whereby wee cry Abba father.</hi> And thirdly it is a name of prouidence, <hi>your heauenly father careth for you.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.7.</note> But how come wee to call God by a name of loue,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:14604:113"/>of priuiledge, and of prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; Surely, hee that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to call God father, hath made him our father. <hi>Hee hath giuen vs power,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
                        <hi>to become the ſonnes of God.</hi> In the old law, God is called by the name of Lord, <hi>Ego Dominus,</hi> I the Lord; there his people are called ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; now from the name of the Lord, he is called fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; his people from fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, are become ſonnes, and all by the meanes of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus. Aſcende ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem meum, &amp; patrem veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum:</hi> I go to my father, and your father, my God and your God.</p>
                     <p>Now calling God father, as it is a name of dignitie, (for it is thought to goe well <hi>with the children of a
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:14604:113"/>rich and louing father</hi>) ſo is it a name of duty. And as he hath the properties of a rich and louing father, to loue, to care for, and to pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo ſhould wee haue alſo the quallities, and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of good children, to honour him to ſerue him, and to obey him; leſt it bee ſaid, as it was once of ſome, <hi>Nutriui filios;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eſay 1.2.</note> 
                        <hi>I haue nouriſhed children, and they haue rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led aganiſt me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly as Chriſt called God here by the name and title of a father; ſo in like manner hath he to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of vs his choſen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants, entituled himſelfe by the name of our father: <hi>After this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner pray; Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</hi> And firſt, this may
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:14604:114"/>teach vs, with bouldneſſe to call, and cry vnto God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſo mercifull, ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and ſo carefull a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in all our neceſſities and afflictions <hi>Call vpon me,</hi> (ſayth almighty God.)<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15</note> 
                        <hi>in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, this teacheth vs, when wee pray, to pray all in one. Let not the rich, and mighty therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the poore, and needy; it is the will of our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to haue vs altogether, to call to God our father; why then ſhould any one contemne or diſdaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, this may admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs to loue one another,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:14604:114"/>and to haue a participation, or fellow feeling of the wants, and miſeries of our brethren, according to the counſell of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.16</note> 
                        <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with them that reioyce, weepe with them that weepe, and bee of like affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an other.<note place="margin">Iohn 13.34.35.</note> A new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement I gine you, that ye loue one another. By this ſhall all men know, that you are my Diſciples if ye loue one another.</hi> This ſo commendable a ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue nature her ſelſe hath taught the wiſe men, (euen among the heathen) which were wont to ſay. <hi>Nihiltam eſſe ſecundum Naturam, quam iuuare conſortem nature,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more agreeable to nature, then to helpe them, that pertake with vs in the ſame nature; eſpecially, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:14604:115"/>the creator of nature, hath indued vs with the ſame condition of nature, that no man ſhould ſuffice to himſelfe, without the ayde of another; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee would haue all things to ſtand. <hi>Mutuis aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s,</hi> by mutuall ſuccours, that the very reaſon of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity might inuite vs to mutuall loue.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As your father which is in heauen is mercifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We ſhew God to be a heauenly father, in that we mention him to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. VVee confeſſe what a manner of Father we mean, that is to ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eauenly. Leſt therefore wee ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as degenerate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, let vs alſo be heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. <hi>In heauen.</hi> What more
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:14604:115"/>powerfull, then to haue a father <hi>In heauen,</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howſoeuer wee are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed on earth, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, wee haue a father in heauen. <hi>In heauen:</hi> Then is our inheritance in heauen alſo. <hi>In heauen:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore praying.<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.1</note> 
                        <hi>Wee liſt vp our eyes vnto the hils, from whence commeth our helpe. In heauen:</hi> Not as placing his diuine power onely there, which filleth heauen and earth; but we ſay <hi>In heauen;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there chiefly his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doth appeare, there hee bleſſeth his Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Well then (ſaith S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten</hi>) we haue a father in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen; let vs not cleaue to things here on earth. <hi>Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus Patrem, Inuenimus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam,</hi> wee haue found our
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:14604:116"/>father, wee h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue found our country. Hence wee learne firſt of all, to acknowledge his goodneſſe. Secondly, to haue recourſe to him in the time of neeth; and thirdly, to be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tifull vnto others by his example, who hath beene ſo louing and ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Is mercifull.</head>
                     <p>As wee wiſh that God ſhould be merciful vnto vs, our Sauiour would haue vs to ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>cy vnto our neighbour. And inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de herein conſiſteth the tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite iuſtice, vvith con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>th the whole duty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which willeth vs <hi>Rodd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> vnicui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> quod ſuum eſt,</hi> to giue ouery one his due, to God our ſelves, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
                     <pb n="229" facs="tcp:14604:116"/>
                     <p>Mercy he wils for two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, firſt becauſe we haue alwaies in our eyes thoſe that haue need of mercy; &amp; as we are men, ſo <hi>Nihil hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani, ànobis alienum putemus;</hi> Let vs thinke no humaine accident ſtrange vnto vs. For if it be true that <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nihil aliud eſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem, quam miſeriam &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemitatem,</hi> Man is nothing elſe but miſery and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Surely then there is no man, good or euill, but nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mercy, and that for this cauſe, for that he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but miſery: And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prouerbe <hi>Miſeria res eſt digna miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia,</hi> Miſerie is a thing worthy of mercy; becauſe <hi>Miſericordia non cauſam, ſed fortunam ſpectat;</hi> mercy loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:14604:117"/>not into the cauſe, but to the preſent ſtate, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. And therefore <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> thus defineth mercy. <hi>Miſericordia eſt alienamiſeria in noſtro corde compaſſio;</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is a fellow feeling in our hearts of anothers miſerie. Mercy, (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) hath the denomination, and ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology <hi>a miſero corde</hi> from a miſerable, or wofull hart; becauſe as often as wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould a man in miſery, the minde through commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being touched with griefe at his miſeries, doth as it were <hi>(cor miſerum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere)</hi> vex and torment the heart, with a ſympathy and fellow feeling of his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And hee that hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of a wretched though wicked man, <hi>non
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:14604:117"/>mores eius, ſed hominem miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi> doth not pittie the manners, (which are euill) but the man, who by being ſinfull, is alſo miſerable. We commend them that loue men, (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) If it be but as they are men; and therefore being on a time reproued, for that hee gaue an almes to a wicked man, anſwered, <hi>Miſertus ſum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem, non Iniquitatem.</hi> I had compaſſion on the man, and not on his manners. <hi>Homo qui Calamitoſo eſt miſericors, meminit ſuit</hi> he that hath pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vpon a man in miſery, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth himſelfe, <hi>Cuiuis poteſt accidere, quod cuiquam accidit.</hi> That which chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vnto one man, may happen alſo to another. So that nothing ſhould more
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:14604:118"/>incline our hearts vnto mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then the conſideration of our owne miſery. And hee that is mercifull, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth mercy againe, when he falleth into miſery. <hi>Habet in aduerſis auxilia, qui in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis commodat;</hi> He findeth ſuccour in aduerſity, which ſheweth the ſame in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, (ſaith <hi>Publius</hi>).</p>
                     <p>The ſecond reſpect, why God willeth mercy, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to him it is more agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and more acceptable; for by it, wee are moſt like him, and by likeneſſe wee beſt pleaſe him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.9</note> 
                        <hi>His mercy is aboue all his workes.</hi> VVell wils he therefore that man being the beſt of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhould be like him, in the beſt of his actions, as plainely appeareth by this
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:14604:118"/>text: <hi>Ye ſhall therefore be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, as your father which is in heauen is mercifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He bids vs not to imitate his power, which <hi>Lucifer</hi> proudly aſpiring to was deiected into hell, nor his wiſdome which <hi>Adam</hi> vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affecting, was elected out of Paradice; but his mercy, which wee humbly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſhal be erected and lifted vp to heauen.</p>
                     <p>Now that wee may bee mercifull, let vs firſt learne who are miſerable. <hi>Not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one that is ſicke, or hungry, or naked, or in priſon;</hi> is ſimply or onely the obiect of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: but many that are alſo ſtrong in body, fat with cheere, braue with cloathes, rich in Lands, and free from bonds: thoſe are ſicke in
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:14604:119"/>ſoule, empty in ſpirit, bare in minde, poore in vertue, ſlaues to ſinne. For as there is a corporall neceſſity, ſo there is a ſpirituall miſery; and in both there is a work of mercy; in the one, the rich ſeeing the want of the poore, may pitty him; in the other, not knowing his owne, may bee pittied of him; in that the diſtreſſed hath nothing but what hee receiues; in this hee hath ſomewhat of his owne to beſtow; there a Potentate may ſhew his bounty, here a beggar may giue <hi>Caeſar</hi> an almes: ſo then there is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the bodie, mercie to the ſoule, and he that doth either, ſhall haue mercie both for body and ſoule: that conſiſts in thoſe ſeauen
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:14604:119"/>works aforenamed, viſiting the ſicke, giuing drinke to the thirſty, bread to the hungry, redeeming the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, cloathing the naked, lodging the ſtranger, and burying the dead. But this hath as many formes of pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as there be acts of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; and all, or more then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> aſcribes to it, is true of this:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.4.</note> 
                        <hi>It giues, it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giues, it enioyeth not, it boaſts not, diſdaines not, ſeekes not her owne, is not angry, thinkes no euill, reioyceth not iniquity, ſuffers all things belecues all things, hopes all things, indures all things.</hi> And to conclude, it doth all things that may bee done, though for a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for a ſtranger, for an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie; as our deare Lord, by conuerſing with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:14604:120"/>of ſinners; in the precedent verſe teacheth vs <hi>To be good with the euill,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 6.35.</note> 
                        <hi>and kind to the vnkinde:</hi> not as proud Pharifies, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or condemning thoſe that erre in life or beliefe; but ſometimes inſtructing, otherwhiles admoniſhing, vpon occaſion tollerating, if neede be, reprouing, and when it is requifite, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Thus to be a <hi>Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> no hypocriſie, but perfect pietie. And though perhaps there bee not alwayes effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting meanes, yet God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reiects a charitable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; it is the mind, not the gift; the will, not the worke, the affection, not the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that God eſteemes: and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth the Corinthians,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:14604:120"/>
                        <hi>For that they had begunne not onely to doe, but alſo to will:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note> for there may bee a doing of good, and no good will; there may be giuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charity, and curteſie without mercy. In ſome, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſhion, not compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or humour, not vertue, or hypocriſie, not Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, produceth ſtrained, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, maimed acts of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
                     <p>Such a giuer doth but caſt off his ſuperfluity ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; hut the truly compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate <hi>(like the widdow)</hi> puts into Gods treaſury of his ſubſtance really; the one giues externally, the other giues internally. As Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, he giues <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ſemetipſum;</hi> Somewhat without himſelfe; this, <hi>de
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:14604:121"/>ſemetipſo,</hi> a peece of himſelf. And albeit this kinde of mercy be moſt vſuall, when it meeteth with vnderſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued miſery, yet muſt there be a pitty, euen of a iuſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, both in priuat men, that in others, ſee daily Gods righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in Magiſtrates, that vſually puniſh male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours: vnleſſe the fault be out of meaſure, ſome heynous offence, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, or his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wherein to be merciful were to be miſerable, and to be compaſſionate, very vniuſt.</p>
                     <p>Let vs not therfore grieue, yea let vs rather reioyce with a great and vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioy, when traytors,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:14604:121"/>murtherers, or the like are worthily brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10</note> 
                        <hi>Seeing mercy and truth they then doe meete, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and peaoe therein kiſſe one another.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But in regard of our own priuate wronges, wee are taught to loue our enemies, <hi>To bleſſe them that curſe vs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 5.44, 45.</note> 
                        <hi>and to doe good to them, that hate vs, and to pray for them, which hurt vs, and perſecute vs, that wee may be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of our Father which is in Heauen; for hee maketh the ſunne to ariſe on the euill, and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt, and on the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let vs not ſo feaſt the body onely that the ſoule ſhould faſt; as many doe, who are mercifull but in
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:14604:122"/>part; Yea, in regard of the ſoule, they are altogether mercileſſe. For what good doe theſe men towards the redemption of a ſoule from the bondage of ſinne and Sathan, more then they doe to a dog, a horſe, or a hog; yet as the miſeries of the ſoule are more dangerous, ſo ſhould they more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be regarded &amp; pittied. Let vs not (<hi>whilſt we carefully feed the ſoule,</hi> ſuffer the body to pine in want and penury; as alſo ſome do who being ouer-clogged with the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall affayres of this life, may not part with a penny what neede ſocuer ſhould be. Howbeit, as man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of ſoule and body, and is ſubiect to miſeries in them both; ſo muſt wee be
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:14604:122"/>charitable to him, in relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of both.</p>
                     <p>If you aske (ſaith <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius)</hi> why God created the world? It was becauſe man ſhould be created. If you demaund why man was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated? It was, becauſe hee ſhould worſhip his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; If you aſke why hee ſhould worſhip his creator? It was, for no other cauſe, but that he might be rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by him. Theſe are the bowels of Gods mercy, who had no other cauſe of his mercy, but his mercy; no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, but his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and our good; wherein there is no end of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, no number of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, no meaſure of his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, no depth of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whoſe great loue to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:14604:123"/>was apparent in this, when he purchaſed our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, with the effuſion of the moſt precious blood of his deere &amp; onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne.</p>
                     <p>And therfore (ſaith <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>) <hi>ſi tanta in terris morare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fides, quanta merces expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur in Coelis:</hi> were there ſo great faith on earth, as there is reward to be expected in heauen, how great ſhould our loue be one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, to tender the good one of another, &amp; to releeue the wants, and neceſſities one of another.</p>
                     <p>And ſurely man hath but two pleas before the throne of Gods iudgement ſeate, the one of Innocency, the other of mercy; the former neuer any <hi>(that Immaculate Lambe, excepted)</hi> could
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:14604:123"/>plead; &amp; what intereſt ſhall man challenge in the plea of mercy, who hath denied the ſame to his brother. For ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 18.33.</note> 
                        <hi>oughteſt not thou alſo to haue had pitty on thy fellow, euen as I had pitty on thee? Let vs then,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2.</note> 
                        <hi>ſo many as bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God the father. Set I ſay your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on things which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and not on things which are on earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Worldly minded men fitly reſemble the earth in theſe fiue points; firſt the nature of the earth is cold and dry, ſo are all worldly affections to deuotion and charity. Secondly the earth ſtandeth ſtill, and hath the
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:14604:124"/>circumfere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce carried round about it; ſo are Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites about earthly men, and they are not at all mooued. Thirdly, the earth doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntimes keepe downe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hot exhalations, which naturally would aſcend; ſo doe worldly affections, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny charitable motions. Fourthly, the earth is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, and heauie things goe downeward; ſo worldly men ſet all their affections onely vpon the terreſtriall things of this life; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18, 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>They are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is damnation, whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is to their ſhame, who minde earthly things.</hi> Laſtly yet the earth is fruitfull after
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:14604:124"/>tilling and manuring; ſo to conclude, till the heart of man be fully manured with the graces of Gods holy Spirit, it can bring forth no good fruite of deuotion &amp; charitie. Let our compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therefore ſo largely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelfe towards the conſolation of others, as in like manner we would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the hands of the Almightie towards our ſelues, ending with this of our Sauiour. <hi>Let vs be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, as our heauenly Father is mercifull.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now the God of grace &amp; mercy, ſo guide you in the wayes of holineſſe &amp; good workes, that both in life &amp; death you may glorifie God your creator, to whom with the Sonne and holy
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:14604:125"/>Spirit, be giuen and aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, from the bottome of our hearts, all power, praiſe, might maieſty and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, both now and for euer. Amen.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14604:125"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
